斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到2013至2014秋季学期
Well, welcome everyone to lecture number seven
CS193P第七讲
of CS1973P fall of 2013-14.
今天我们会讲一下输入输出
Today we are going to talk about input and output.
涉及到屏幕上
Okay? It's about views
矩形区域的视图
which you're rectangular areas on the screen
可以在其中绘制自定义内容
that you can use both to draw custom stuff
以及从用户触控手势 多点触控中
and to get gestures in
获取手势
from user touch gestures, multi-touch.
我会用一个示例演示这些内容
I'm going to have a demo that's going to show you all that.
我们会创建一个自定义视图
We're going to build a custom view,
它有自己的自定义手势等等
it's going to have its own custom gestures and all that stuff.
基本上 它会绘制...
It's basically going to draw the--
我们在Machismo中使用的卡牌
you know, the cards that we used in Machismo
都不太好看 比如梅花A
were just really bad, like A clubs.
看起来并不像扑克牌
They didn't look like cards,
所以我们会创建一个自定义视图
so we're going to actually have a custom view
顶角有数字和花色 还有人头牌
Right? Has the things in the corner, and face cards,
这些全套的东西
all that-- that whole business.
视图是iOS中至关重要的一部分
All right, so a view is of critical importance in iOS.
它是所有绘制操作的核心
It's right at the heart of all the drawing we do.
大家已经用过非常多的视图了
You've used a ton of views already.
按钮是视图
Buttons are views.
标签是视图
Labels are views. Okay?
基本上 它是构造块
It's basically the building block
代表屏幕上的一块矩形区域
that represents a rectangular area on screen.
定义了一个坐标空间
It defines a coordinate space.
在这个坐标空间中 你可以进行绘制
Okay? A coordinate space you can draw in.
可以在其中添加触控事件
And a coordinate space that you can get touch events in
掌握它们的位置
and understand where they are.
它是分层级的
It's hierarchical.
可以在视图中嵌套视图
Right? So you can have view inside views,
层层嵌套 明白吗
inside views, all right?
每个视图只有一个父视图
Every view only has one superview.
但是一个特定视图可以有很多子视图
But a given view could have many subviews
而这些子视图就是一个个矩形
and those sub view are just rectangles.
相互之间可以重叠等等
They can overlap, whatever.
不要求它们平铺或相互独立
You know they're not required to somehow be tiled or separate.
特定视图的子视图是完全自由的
They're complete free form subviews of a given view.
一个视图可以有任意多个子视图
You can have any number of subview you want for a given view.
子视图的顺序很重要
The order of the subviews does matter,
因为它们可以是透明的
because they can be transparent.
我们会讲到这部分
We'll talk about that.
还有一点有时会令人困惑就是
And one thing that's sometimes a little confusing is
视图是这个矩形区域
you have this rectangular area that you're view,
但其实可以在区域外进行绘制
but you can actually draw outside that area.
完全合法
Perfectly legal.
Xcode中有一个开关
There is a little switch you can turn on in Xcode
或者说是UIView的一个属性
or obviously a property in UIView
代表"裁剪子视图"
that says "Clips my subviews."
换句话说就是不要让我的子视图
In other words, don't let my subviews go outside my
超出视图边界
my view's bound. Right?
可以按照自己意愿将绘制内容控制在一定范围内
So you can kind of keep things contained if you want, but...
通常这并不是默认值 我们一般也不需要
General that's not the default and generally we don't.
有一个UIWindow类
There is a UIWindow class.
在iOS中并不重要
Very unimportant in iOS.
如果要学习Mac UIWindow就很重要了
If we're on the Mac, UIWindow would matter.
可以在桌面上放置多个窗口
You got a lot of windows on a desktop.
但在iOS中 视图就是主要内容了
But in iOS, it's all about views.
只有一个UIWindow
There's only one UIWindow.
它包括了当前出现在屏幕上的
It's the one that's containing all the views
全部视图
that are currently on screen.
这也就是为什么在上一个示例中 我可以说
That's why in the last demo I was able to say
如果self.view.window不为空 我就知道我正显示在屏幕上
if self.View.Window, then I knew I was on screen.
因为只有这一个窗口
Right? Because that's the only window there is
如果我在窗口中 那么我就是在屏幕上
and so if I am in it then I'm on screen.
所以UIWindow无关紧要
So UIWindow very unimportant,
你甚至用不着
you don't even aver had to
查看UIWindow的文档
look at the documentation for UIWindow.
UIView就是我们需要的全部内容
UIViews are what it's all about.
视图的这种层级结构
So this hierarchy of views.
视图嵌套视图 通常是在Xcode中完成的
View inside views is most often built in Xcode,
只要将视图拖入即可
just by dragging views in.
我们目前还没有做过很多
Now we haven't done a lot of
将视图拖拽到另一个视图中的操作
dragging views inside other views,
但是这样做是完全合法的
but it's perfectly legal to do that
你有时会在Xcode中遇到这种情况
and you'll see in Xcode sometimes
当你拖拽时 系统会想要将它放到另一个视图中
when you drag, it try to drop it in another view.
你也许并不想这样做 但是系统会尝试这样做
You might even don't want it to, but it tries to.
所以很多情况下都会用图形化的方式来创建
So a lot of it would build graphically.
我们还可以通过代码创建
However, we could also build it in code
当我们使用代码
and when we build it in code,
创建和拆解这个新的层级结构时
build and tear down this new hierarchy in code
需要这两个方法 addSubView
with these two methods, addSubView.
和大家想的完全一样
Exactly what you would think.
它得到一个视图
It just takes a view
将它作为子视图添加到另一个视图上
and adds it as a subview of some other view.
将这个方法发送给
You send that to the view
目标父视图
that you want to be the parent view, right.
也就是你想要向其添加子视图的那个视图
That's the view to which you are adding the subview.
相反的操作
On the opposite side,
如果想要将视图从视图层级中移除
to get a view out of the view hierarchy
就要向想要移除的那个视图发送removeFromSuperview
you send removeFromSuperview to the view you want to remove.
而不是发送给它的父视图
Not to it's parent.
所以不能用removeFromSuperview:view
So you don't say removeFromSuperview:view.
只需要对你想要移除的那个视图说
You just say to a view that you want out of there,
从父视图中移除你自己
remove yourself from superview.
所以添加和移除操作中发送方法的对象
Okay, so it's a little different adding and removing
不太一样
who you ask to do it.
这是MVC 所有肯定有视图
You're MVCs, of course have a view.
而MVC的视图层级结构中
And that top level view that contains all the views
包含全部视图的那个顶级视图
in the view hierarchy for your MVC
就是视图控制器中的view视图属性
is the property view in view controller.
所以如果你查看UIViewController
So if you look in UIViewController,
它有一个属性叫做view
there's a property called view.
它是UIView
It's a UIView.
如果你打开Xcode 在控制器上单击右键
And if you go in Xcode and right click on your controller
或者在MVC的视图背景上单击右键
or right click on the background of your MVC's view,
你会看到一个输出口
you'll see an outlet basically.
因为这个view属性确实就是个输出口
Because it's really is an outlet, this view property.
输出口指向顶级视图
And it points to that top level view.
所以如果你想用代码
So that's a good place to start
向视图层级结构中添加视图
if you want to start adding views in code
这是一个很好的出发点
to your view hierarchy.
当然 当你在Xcode中拖出它们时
And of course when you drag them out in Xcode
你就是这样做的
that's what you're doing.
是将它们放在了...
You're dropping them in--
除非你是将它们拖拽到另一个视图上
Unless you're dropping them in on top of another view,
否则你就是将视图放到了背景中 self.view中
you're dropping into that background, the self.view.
self.view
Okay, self.View.
我们用self.view来表示 将视图放在self.view中
We use that phrase self.view, it puts in self.view.
self.view是UIViewController的顶级UIView
Self.View is that top level UIView in UIViewController.
它只是一个普通的UIView
It's just a plain UIView.
并不是子类
It's not a subclass version.
我们永远都不会子类化这个视图
You never subclass that view.
它就像是一个大的容器视图
It's just kind of a big container view.
这是另外一件需要知道的关于视图的事情
And that's another thing to know about views,
绘制或处理触控事件时并不经常需要对其进行子类化
you don't always subclass them to draw or do touch events.
有时它们只是边界
Sometimes they're just boundaries. Right?
只是用来定义一个坐标空间
Just a view you want to define a coordinate space
在其中增加其他视图
and you want to put some other views inside of it.
完全没问题 可以这样做
Perfectly fine, we do that.
初始化UIView
So initializing a UIView.
更常见的是
A little more common to want to
在子类中 重写UIView的
override the designated initializer of a UIView
指定初始化方法
in a subclass.
还记得吗 在UIViewController中我们说
Remember in UIViewController we kind of said,
我们几乎从来不会这样做
we almost never do that
因为UIViewController通常都会从storyboard中创建
because UIViewController are almost always coming out of storyboards.
所以指定初始化方法永远都不会被调用
So the designated initializer never gets called in anyway.
我们只要用awakeFromNib方法
So we just do awakeFromNib.
而不用initWithNibName bundle
Okay? And we never do that initWithNibName bundle thing.
UIView中并不是这样的
That's not true in UIView.
在UIView中 你不仅需要
In UIView you do more often both need to do something
在初始化方法中做些操作
in your initializer and just want to, you know,
需要初始化方法 并在其中添加代码
have your initializer around and code in there.
但当你这样做时 你仍需要awakeFromNib
So but when you do it, you want to also do awakeFromNib.
因为创建UIView的两种方法是同等的
Okay? That's because UIViews are equally created--
也不是完全同等 但至少是两种常用的方法
well, not equally, but at least they're commonly created
一种是将它们拖进storyboard中
both by dragging them into a storyboard,
对应的就是awakeFromNib初始化
so that would be the awakeFromNib initialization
另外一种是向它们发送alloc/init
and by sending alloc and init to them.
也就是说在代码中创建一个视图
In other words, in your code creating a view.
比如 在作业中
So for example, in your homework you're going to
大家需要实现设置卡牌和真正的扑克牌
have to do set cards and playing cards for real,
不再是按钮 而是真正地绘制出来
not as buttons, but actually drawing them
几乎可以肯定 你会用allco/init来初始化这些视图
and you will almost certainly be allocating those views
因为视图数量不确定
because there can be-- there's not a fixed number of them
所以你并不能完全用在Xcode中拖出来实现
so you can't really drag them out in Xcode
因为它们需要出现和消失
because they have to come and go.
大家要实现这部分内容
So you'll be doing that.
这和我们对UIViewController做过的操作类似
So we do the same kind of thing we did with UIViewController.
添加一个setup方法
Right? Where we have some kind of setup method.
方法名可以是setup或者其他的
You can call it setup thing or whatever you want.
然后在awakeFromNib中调用它
And then you call it from awakeFromNib
还要从UIView的指定初始化方法中调用它
and then you also call it from UIView's designated initializer
指定初始化方法叫做initWithFrame
which is called initWithFrame.
Frame框架指定了该视图
And that frame specifies where this view is
在其父视图坐标系中的位置
in its superview's coordinate system.
是该视图的位置信息
It's the positioning of this view.
代码就是这个样子的
Okay? So that's what the code would look like.
就像这样
Just like that.
加上初始化代码
Put your initialization codes inside.
我们会在示例中进行演示
And we'll do that in the demo just so you see that.
在继续讲解UIView的
Now before I can talk more about UIView
绘制和获取事件之前
and drawing there and getting events,
我们需要先定义几个类型
we got to define a few types here.
一个是CGFloat
One is CGFloat.
它是一个浮点数
It's a floating point number.
在屏幕上绘制图形 获取触控事件等
All floating point numbers that have to do with
所用到的全部浮点数
drawing on the screen or getting touch events or whatever
都是CGFloat
are CGFloats.
它可能是一个double类型
This might be a double.
可能只是一个普通的浮点数
It might be just a regular floating point number.
可能是32位 64位
It might be 32 bits, 64 bits.
我们不知道 也不在意
You don't know and you don't care
但你始终需要使用CGFloat
but you always have to use CGFloat.
不只是用CGFloat来指定屏幕上的位置等
Not only using CGFloat to specify positions on screen and all the things
如果你要对屏幕上的数字
but if you're going to be multiplying or adding numbers
做乘法或加法
to things that are on screen
重新计算得到新值
to recalculate new things, all--
这些都要用CGFloat
you want to do all that in the CGFloat domain.
所以处理屏幕事件时
So you're going to have a lot of
很多属性和局部变量
properties and local variables that are CGFloats
都是CGFloat类型
when you're doing screen stuff. Okay?
还有一个C结构体叫做CGPoint
Then there's a c-struct called CGPoint.
其中有两个元素 x和y
That has just got two elements in it. X and y.
分别代表X轴和Y轴的位置
That's an X and Y position.
在绘制范围内
Okay? In the drawing world.
还有一个结构体叫做CGSize
And there's CGSize which is just a struct
包含宽度和高度 也都是CGFloat
with width and height which are both CGFloats also.
指定了宽度和高度
And that's just specifying a width and height.
还有CGRect
And then there's CGRect
这个C结构体包含了另外两个CG结构体
which is c-struct with those other two CG structs in them.
CGPoint和CGSize
CGPoint and CGSize.
指定了一个矩形的原点
That specifies an origin
以及宽度和高度
and a width and height for a rectangle.
大家要知道这四个结构体
Okay? So you've got to know these four.
当我们在屏幕上进行绘制时
I'm going to refer these left, right and center
我会用到左 右 中间
whenever we're drawing on screen,
说的就是这些结构体
this is what we're talking about.
绘制或处理事件所用的视图坐标系中
Okay? The origin of a views coordinate system
原点是左上角
for drawing or for handling events is upper left.
不是左下角
Now lower left.
与笛卡儿坐标系不同
Not like Cartesian coordinates. Okay?
这里是从左上角开始绘制
This is drawing from the upper left.
所以Y值越大 屏幕上的位置越靠下
So positive Y values are down the screen.
大家可以看到 我在那里放的那个点是(400,35)
Okay? So you can see I put that point up there 400,35.
就是X和Y轴的值 X是向右400
That's X and Y. X is 400 way over to the right
Y是正数35
and 35 is Y and positive
所以是从左上角原点向下
so it's down from that origin on the upper left. Okay?
绘制的单位都是点 而非像素点
The units in all this drawing are points, not pixels.
原因可能大家已经明白了
Okay? Probably you already understand why this is，
因为有些设备的像素很高
because some devices have lots of pixels.
像素点排列非常密集
Right? I mean it's very high density pixeled
比如Retina显示屏
like these retina displays.
而有些设备 比如iPad和旧款的iPhone
Other ones like some of the iPads, older iPhones,
它们的像素点没有那么多和密集
they don't have as many-- they're not as dense of pixels.
如果不用点来作为单位 而是用像素点
Well if we didn't use points, if we used pixels
那么像素点小的时候
then things we drew would be really small
我们绘制的内容就会很小
if the pixels were small
如果像素点大 绘制的内容就会很大
and really big if the pixels were big.
所以我们简化一下 使用点来作为绘制单位
So we abstract that away by using points.
要知道你的视图所在的显示器上
Okay? How many pixels per point are
每个点中有多少像素点
on the display that your view is in.
可以通过UIView的这个属性
You can find out by using this UIView property
contentScaleFactor来获得
contentScaleFactor.
如果是Retina显示屏 返回值为2
So it returned two for example on a retina display
因为Retina显示屏上每点包括两个像素点
because there are two pixels per point on a retina display.
而在非Retina屏的iPad上则返回1
One on a non-retina iPad for example.
在我们这门课上 这个学期中
You know, probably not going to need to use that property
我们可能用不到这个属性
in this class, this quarter.
上个学期我们用到了它
Previous quarter we played around with it,
但是这个学期不需要了
but not this quarter.
更重要的是 这些属性
But more importantly, there are these properties
说明了绘制系统的位置和范围
that talk about the position and extent of your drawing system.
明白吗
Okay?
理解这些属性间的不同
It's really important to understand the difference
是非常重要的
between these properties.
首先是这个CGRect属性bounds
First you have this CGRect property bounds.
这是你的坐标系中绘制区域的原点
That is the origin and width and height of the drawing area
以及宽度和高度
in your own coordinate system.
你自己的坐标系
Your own coordinate system.
在其中绘制和处理触控事件
A system you are drawing in and handling touch events in.
底下的CGRect frame
Okay? CGRect frame at the bottom there,
指的是你的父视图坐标系中的一个矩形
that is a rectangle that completely contains you
这个矩形完全包含了你的绘制区域
in your superview's coordinate system.
可以看到它是如何定位你的
So you can see how that positions you.
因为它在你的父视图坐标系中
Right? Because that's in your superview's coordinate system.
也就是你所在的位置
That's where you are.
center代表你在父视图坐标系中
Okay? Center is just the center of where you are
所在位置的中心
in your superview's coordinate system.
没有属性能够得到
There's no property to get your center
你在自己的坐标系中的中心位置
in your own coordinate system.
只要得到bounds
You just take your bounds out
宽度和高度分别除以二
width divide it by two and height divide it by two
就可以得到中心位置了
and boom you're in the middle.
你可能会认为frame和bounds
Okay? Now you might think frame and bounds
是完全一样的
are going to be exactly the same,
除了一点不同
except for that the frame is going to be
frame是在父视图坐标系中的
in the superview's coordinate system,
所以二者的原点可能不同
so the origins might be different.
但并不是这样的
But that's not true.
因为视图可以旋转
Okay? And the reason for that is that views can be rotated.
视图旋转后 可以看到
Okay? And if a view is rotated you can see that
包含它的那个矩形会变大很多
the rectangle that contains it might be much bigger.
因为要包含的是一个菱形
Right? Because it's a diamond shape that it has to contain.
幻灯片中这里还有些具体数据
Okay? So there's details on here in this slide.
大家有空可以看一下
You can look at them at your leisure,
但是至少要理解
but bottom line is understand
frame是在你的父视图坐标系中
that frame is a rectangle containing you
包含你的一个矩形
in your superview's coordinate system,
bounds是你在自己的视图中
bounds is the rectangle you use to draw
用自己的代码进行绘制时使用的矩形
when you're drawing in your own code in your view.
是在你自己的坐标系中
It's your coordinate system.
请讲
Yeah?
bounds的原点何时不为(0,0)呢
When would the origins of bounds not be zero zero?
bounds的原点什么时候不是(0,0)呢
When did the origins of bounds not be zero zero?
非常棒的问题
That's an excellent question.
因为是你自己的坐标系
The origin of the bounds,
所以bounds的原点
since it's your own coordinate system
取决于你的解释
is up to your own interpretation.
比如滚动视图中的原点
So for example scroll view uses the origin to say
代表滚动目标的位置
where am I looking in the thing I'm scrolling on?
它就是这样定义原点的
That's just the way it defines origin.
你可以根据需要 定义原点的含义
You can define what you want origin to mean.
因为要求你进行绘制
Okay? Because you're going to be asked to draw
而你知道自己的坐标系
and you know your own coordinate systems.
无论要求你绘制什么 你都要绘制出来
You're gonna draw whatever you're asked to draw.
所以基本取决于你
So it's kind of up to you.
99%的情况下 原点都是(0,0)
99% of the time, your origin is zero zero.
因为它对你来说没有什么意义
Because it doesn't mean anything for you.
宽度和高度才是重要的
It's just the width and height that matter.
这个问题非常好
But that's a great question.
大家可以再看看幻灯片 获取细节内容
Okay? So again, you can look at the slide for more detail
但是一定要理解frame和bounds
but frame and bounds just make sure you understand that.
创建视图的方法
So most often you create views
通常是从Xcode的面板中拖出
by dragging them out of the palette in Xcode
方法和拖出标签
and that's like when you're dragging out labels,
按钮 滚动视图和文本视图一样
and buttons, and scroll views, and text views.
它们都是视图
Those are all views.
直接拖出它们就可以进行创建
So you just create them by dragging out
甚至还可以拖出你的自定义视图
and you could even drag out your own custom views.
但是方法是先拖出一个通用视图
But the way you do that is you drag out a generic view,
然后转到标识符检查器 修改它的类
and then go to the identity inspector and change its class.
和拖出视图控制器的方法一样
Exactly like how we drag out a view controller.
我们需要把它的类修改为某个自定义类
We have to go change its class to be one of our custom classes. Right?
因为Xcode显然不知道我们的自定义类
Because Xcode obviously doesn't know our custom classes.
至少在storyboard中运行时
At least doesn't know in the kind of runtime way
它不知道
that's happening in the storyboard,
所以我们需要手动设置
so we have to set the things.
和设置视图控制器是完全一样的
It works exactly the same as setting view controllers.
在代码中创建视图
Creating a view in code,
也就是说不直接将其拖至storyboard中
in other words not dragging it in to a storyboard.
可以直接用alloc/initWithFrame 或者alloc/init
You just use alloc and initWithFrame or just alloc and init.
如果用alloc/init
It you do alloc and init,
等同于alloc initWithFrame: CGRectZero
that's the same as alloc and initWithFrame CGRectZero,
CGRectZero是一个原点为0
which is a rectangle with origin zero,
宽度和高度为0的矩形
width and height of zero. Okay?
可以任选其一
So you can do either one.
如果要用alloc/init
If you do alloc and init
最好为frame赋值
presumably you better set the frame to something
这样当它被放入父视图中时
so that it knows where to be
才能知道自己要出现在哪里
when it's put into its superview.
这个示例是用代码创建UILabel
So here's an example of creating a UILabel in code.
我这里用的是UILabel initWithFrame
You see I said UILabel initWithFrame.
我向它传递了一个矩形
I gave it a rectangle.
是在父视图坐标系中的
That's in the superview coordinate system.
然后我用addSubview将那个标签添加为self.view的子视图
And then I addSubview that label to self.view
self.view是我的视图控制器中的顶级视图
which is that top level view in my view controller.
所以在我的MVC视图中 它显示在(20,20)的位置
And so it ended up at 20, 20, 20 X and 20 Y,
宽度为50 高度为30
and its 50 wide and 30 high in my MVC's view. Right?
你可能不会这样创建标签
Now you probably wouldn't ever create a label like this
因为可以直接拖出标签
because you drag them out.
但是你可能会这样创建自己的自定义视图
But you might create your own custom view like this. Right?
什么时候需要创建自定义视图呢
Okay, so when do I want to create my own custom views?
显然是当我想绘制一些自定义内容的时候
Obviously, when I want to draw something custom.
按钮或标签无法绘制出的内容
Not something that a button or a label can draw for me.
或者是当我要处理特殊触控事件时
Or when I want to handle special touch events.
滑动 捏合之类的
Swipes, or pinches, or something like that.
我们先介绍绘制部分
So the drawing side of this which we'll talk about first
这部分非常简单
is really easy.
UIView中有一个方法叫做drawRect
There's one method in UIView called drawRect
你只要实现这个方法
and all you have to do is implement that method
就可以绘制想要的内容
to draw what you want.
只要这一个方法就够了
Okay? One method, that's it.
实现这个方法来绘制想要的内容
Implement this method to draw what you want.
它有一个参数
Now it has that argument there,
是一项性能优化
that's a performance optimization.
代表一个矩形说
That's basically a rectangle that says,
你绘制吧 但是我只需要坐标系中
well, please draw yourself but really I only need the stuff
这个矩形范围内的内容
that's in the rectangle in your coordinate system.
但如果你不想管这个矩形
But if you want to ignore this rectangle
想随意绘制 我觉得没问题
and draw all over yourself, that's fine by me.
它只是为了优化性能
Okay? So it's purely performance thing.
对于某些视图 只考虑这个矩形是有意义的
Some views it'll make sense to look at that rectangle
会非常有效率
and be really efficient.
几年前 这门课布置过一个作业
Like we had an assignment a couple years ago in this class
需要绘制一条曲线
where you're drawing a graph.
如果你是在绘制曲线
Well, if you're drawing a graph
需要计算每一个点
and you're having to calculate every point
如果只需要计算曲线某一段上的点
it's kind of nice to only have to calculate the points
而不是每次都绘制全部曲线
in some part of the graph
是很好的
instead of drawing the whole thing every time.
但是如果你要绘制的是扑克牌
But if you're drawing a playing card,
只需要很少的资源
it's so light weight to draw it,
可以全部都绘制出来
so you can just draw all the parts of it.
不需要使用这个矩形
You don't have to use the rectangle.
如果在矩形外面绘制
If you draw outside of the rectangle
会显示出来吗
does that stuff show up?
问题是 如果在矩形外面绘制
The question is if you draw outside the rectangle
会显示出来吗
does that show up?
记住 所有绘制内容都会显示出来
Remember that everything you draw shows up
除非用了之前讲到的裁剪
unless you have one of these clipping things I talked about
父视图对你进行了裁剪
where your superview is clipping you
或者绘制的一部分是裁剪矩形
or you have a clip rect as part of what you draw.
答案是 这个矩形和裁剪毫无关系
So the answer is that rectangle has nothing to do with clipping.
无论这个矩形是什么
Okay? No matter what that rectangle is,
是否裁剪都是不受影响的
clipping or not is unaffected.
只是为了性能优化
It's purely performance--
提示你什么内容需要重新绘制
giving you a hint of what needs to be redrawn.
就是这样
That's all it is.
非常重要的一点是 绝不要调用drawRect
So really important, never call drawRect.
如果你在作业中调用了drawRect
If you called drawRect in a homework assignment in this class
就等着挨批吧
you are going to get dinged.
因为我在这里用红色字体写了 绝对不要
Because I'm putting it in red, never red.
绝对不要调用drawRect
And I'm telling you don't ever call drawRect.
drawRect是由系统来调用的
DrawRect is for the system to call.
如果你想要重绘视图
Okay? If you want your view redrawn
就调用setNeedsDisplay
you call the method setNeedsDisplay.
它会告诉系统 这个视图需要被重绘
That tells the system this view needs to be redrawn,
然后系统会在合适的时间
and then the system will call drawRect
调用drawRect
at an appropriate time.
系统知道在什么时间
Okay? The system knows when it's an appropriate time
调用drawRect 更新屏外缓冲器
to call drawRect, update offscreen buffers,
完成全部所需操作
whatever the heck it has to do.
它来负责
It's in control of that.
不要自己调用drawRect
Don't ever call drawRect.
调用drawRect是不会起作用的
It just will not work to call drawRect. Okay?
要调用setNeedsDisplay
SetNeedsDisplay.
你可以调用setNeedsDisplayInRect
And you can do setNeedsDisplayInRect,
传给它那个优化矩形
that's giving the little optimization rect. Okay?
要调用setNeedsDisplay来实现
But setNeedsDisplay is how you do that. Okay?
那么如何实现drawRect呢
All right so, how do I implement this drawRect thing?
我有这个drawRect方法
Okay, I got this drawRect method.
想要绘制一些内容
I want to draw something.
方法是使用这个Quartz库
Well, the answer is you use this library, the Quartz library
叫做Core Graphics
that's called Core Graphics.
Core Graphics
Core Graphics.
其中有很多C函数
It has a ton of C functions
函数名以Core Graphics的缩写CG开头
that all start with CG, Core Graphics.
几乎全部都以context上下文作为第一个参数
They almost all take in context as the first argument.
我们会讲到的
We'll talk about that.
还可以用这个类 UIBezierPath
Or you can use this nice class called the UIBezierPath.
UIBezierPath可以将各种复杂形状
UIBezierPath let's you build all these complicated shapes
组成一个大的路径
into a big path,
然后你可以在屏幕上对其进行描边或填充
and then you can stroke it or fill it on screen.
我们详细讲一下
Okay, so let's look into these.
想要理解这些内容 我们需要先理解一下
To understand these we need to understand a little bit
Core Graphics的工作思路
about how Core Graphics thinks
它是按照下面四步进行的
and it thinks in the following four step process.
你需要有一个绘制的上下文
You got to have a context to draw in.
你需要创建路径 三角形 正方形
You got to create paths: triangle, squares, whatever,
圆角矩形等等
rounded rect, whatever it might be.
然后设置你想要的颜色 字体
Then you set the colors and the fonts you want to use,
线宽等等
and line widths and all that stuff.
然后对刚才创建的路径进行描边或填充
And then you stroke or fill the paths that you created.
这是Core Graphics的基本流程
This is the fundamental way Core Graphics goes.
我们具体讲一下这些内容
Okay? So let's talk about all those things.
UIBezierPath封装了
UIBezierPath by the way encapsulates all --
全部上述操作
doing all of that.
帮你处理好了上下文
It takes care of the context for you.
你不用费心去想它
So you don't even have to think about that.
创建路径的方法就是
You create paths by sending messages to the UA--
向UIBezierPath实例发送消息
to a UIBezierPath instance.
它允许你设置颜色 线宽等等
It let's you set colors and line widths and all that
然后调用它的方法进行描边和填充
and then it has methods to stroke and fill.
它封装了全部上述机制
So it encapsulates all that mechanism.
我们来讲讲上下文
So let's talk about the context.
通常情况下 你不用考虑上下文
Mostly you don't have to worry about context
因为要用UIBezierPath
because you're going to use UIBezierPath.
我会演示一个方法 可以使用CG函数
I'll show you a way if you're using the CG functions
获取在屏幕上绘制的上下文
to get the context to draw on screen.
上下文代表的是绘制的位置
But a context means where am I drawing in terms of--
我现在是在屏幕上绘制吗
am I drawing on screen right now?
还是绘制在屏外位图上呢
Am I drawing off screen, in some bitmap?
绘制的内容创建为PDF文件吗
Am I creating a PDF file out of what I'm drawing?
是否绘制输出至打印机呢
Am I drawing to a printer?
iOS可以很好地支持打印机操作
iOS has great printing support
所以你可以将绘制的图像
so you could be drawing to print a page
通过Air Print打印机之类的打印出来
on an Air Print printer or something like that.
这就是context上下文
So that's the context part of it.
对于一般绘制 UIKit会在调用drawRect前
For normal drawing, UIKit sets this context up for you
替你设置这个上下文
before it calls drawRect.
当执行drawRect时 上下文就可以使用了
And then once you're in drawRect, context is ready to go.
UIBezierPath知道它是什么
UIBezierPath knows what it is,
如果你想调用CG函数
and if you want to call the CG functions
就调用这个方法UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext
you call this method UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext.
如果在drawRect中调用这个方法
If you call this inside your drawRect
你会得到一个cookie
you'll get a little cookie
将它作为第一个参数
that you can hand off as the first argument
传递给Core Graphic函数
to all these CG, you know, Core Graphic functions. Okay?
这些CG函数并不常用
And you're not gonna need those CG functions very much.
只有当UIBezierPath无法实现目标功能时才会用到
Only when UIBezierPath won't do what you want,
非常少见
which is pretty rare.
这是个神奇的东西
Okay? So this is the magic thing.
CGContextRef是一个无类型指针
That context ref is just a void star.
你不知道它是什么
You don't know what it is.
它是不透明的
It's opaque.
每次调用drawRect时都会新建它
And this thing is new every time your drawRect is called,
所以不要一直保存着它
so never keep that thing around.
它只在drawRect调用期间有效
It's only good from the start of your drawRect to the end.
不要把它保存在属性等始终有效的元素内
Don't keep it in a property or anything that's going to live.
每次使用drawRect时
Okay? Call the UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext
调用UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext
each time you start a drawRect.
如何定义路径呢
Okay, so how do we define a path?
假设我们想用UIBezierPath绘制三角形
So let's say we wanted to do a triangle with UIBezierPath.
我们这样对UIBezierPath进行分配和初始化
We alloc and init UIBezierPath like this.
移动至起始点
We move to where our starting point is.
我要移动到上面的那个点
So I'm going to move to the top there.
向右75 向下10
75 across and 10 down.
然后添加一条直线至下面这个点
Then I'm going to add a line to that point
向右160 向下150
going down to over to 160 down to 150.
再添加一条线到左边(10,150)这点
I'll add another line to come back to 10, 150.
然后调用closePath方法封闭路径
And then I'm going to close this path, by calling closePath--
再添加一条线回到起始点
that goes back to where we-- draws a line where we started.
得到了一个好看的三角形
So I have a nice triangle there.
我这样讲有点误导大家
Now I'm kind of misleading you,
因为在调用UIBezierPath的这些方法时
because as I'm making all those calls in UIBezierPath,
实际上什么都不会发生
nothing is actually happening.
屏幕是空的
Okay? The screen is blank.
我刚才的这些操作只是在UIBezierPath中
Okay? Because all I'm doing here is building that path up
创建绘制路径
in that UIBezierPath.
我还没有真正进行绘制
I haven't actually draw it yet.
当真正要绘制时
When I want to actually draw it
需要设置填充颜色和描边颜色
I have to set my fill color and stroke color
方法是调用...
and you can do that by calling--
向一个UIColor发送setFill和setStroke
sending setFill and setStroke to a UIColor.
获取UIColor的方法和属性化字符串那里的操作一样
Just get a UIColor like you did for attributed string, whatever.
一样的
UIColor, Same thing.
调用setFill和setStroke
Call setFill or setStroke.
甚至可以直接用set
You can even just say set
它会将填充颜色和描边颜色
and it'll set the fill and the stroke
都设为你选定的颜色
to be whatever color you're sent it to.
设置好填充和描边颜色之后
And once you have your color for fill and stroke set
向路径发送一条fill填充消息
you send a message to the path saying fill
或者发送一条stroke描边消息
and or message to the path saying stroke.
这时它才会真正进行绘制
And now it will actually draw.
最后的fill和stroke这两个调用
So those last two calls there, fill and stroke.
才是真正开始绘制
Those are the things that cause drawing to happen.
之前其他操作都类似于准备工作
Okay? Everything else is just like setup.
明白吗
Make sense?
这些看起来好像很简单 三角形
Okay. Now this might all seem like whoa, triangle great
我可以绘制一个三角形
and I can draw a triangle.
听起来很容易
Sounds easy.
但是实际上 UIBezierPath可以实现很多操作
But there's actually a lot the UIBezierPath can do
比这复杂得多
that's really much more sophisticated than that.
你还可以设置线宽等等
You can set your line widths and things like that
让你的图像...
to make your drawing, you know,
可以设置图案等等
you can set patterns and all kinds of that
让绘制图像更加有趣
to make them more interesting.
UIBezierPath还有很多很棒的函数
And also UIBezierPath has a lot of cool functions
比如bezierPathWithRoundedRect cornerRadius
like bezierPathWithRoundedRect cornerRadius.
它会给你一个路径
Okay? And that will give you a path,
是一个圆角矩形
which is a rounded rectangle
在特定的bounds内
in its... inside of a certain bounds.
还有很多类似的函数
Okay? And it has a bunch of other ones similar to that.
这样你就可以构建更复杂的图形
So that you can build more complicated things
不再只是一条条直线连接起来
than line to line to line to.
我演示刚才的例子 只是因为它比较简单
Okay? I just show you that because it's simple.
下面这是创建椭圆形的示例
Right? So that's how you would for example create an oval.
你还可以用UIBezierPath来裁剪绘图
You can also use UIBezierPath to clip your drawing.
这非常重要
This is super important.
你们的作业需要用到它
You will need this for your homework I think.
我觉得应该有不用它完成作业的方法
I supposed there's a way to do the homework without this
但是我想不出来
but I can't think of a way.
我可以 但是会非常冗长乏味
Well, I can but it would be extremely tedious.
比如圆角矩形
Rounded rect for example
就可以用来裁剪绘图
could be used to clip your drawing.
所以如果你想绘制某种图案
So if you wanted to draw some kind of pattern
但是想让它出现在一个圆角矩形内
but you wanted it to be inside a rounded rect
你只要生成一个圆角矩形
you just get a rounded rect,
就像幻灯片上面的示例那样
just like earlier in the slide there
然后用addClip
and say addClip.
从这里开始
And at that point-- from that point on
你的所有绘图都会被裁剪
all your drawing will be clipped
出现在那个圆角矩形路径内
to be inside that Bezier path.
还可以添加更多裁剪区域
Okay? And there's ways to add more clipping on,
取消裁剪等等
to turn off your clipping, you know, that kind of thing.
所以裁剪也是UIBezierPath中重要的一部分
So clipping is important piece of UIBezierPath as well.
再讲一下如何利用UIView的透明度进行绘制
Okay, let's talk about drawing with transparency in UIView.
默认情况下 UIView是不透明的
Okay, UIViews by default are opaque.
它们有背景色 默认是白色
They have a background color, by default it's white.
所以如果你在屏幕上放一个视图 然后运行
So if you put a view on screen and just run
会出现一个白色的矩形
it'll come out as a white rectangle.
我们并不总是需要这样
Okay? So that's not always what you want.
如果是扑克牌 我想要圆角矩形的
So for example in a playing card I want it to have rounded rects
我希望顶角部分是透明的
and I want those corners to show through.
也许牌桌上有其他牌
Maybe there's a card behind or something on the playing table
被这张牌盖住了之类的
that the card is on or something.
所以我不希望它是不透明的
So I don't want it to be opaque.
在示例中大家会看到
So you're going to see in our demo
我们要关掉这个不透明性
we're going to have to turn this opaqueness off.
实现方法是
The way you turn the opaqueness off
将UIView的属性opaque设置为NO
is you have to set this property opaque in UIView to no.
也就是说 你要告诉系统
In other words you have to tell the system
这个视图不是不透明的
this view is not opaque.
即便你将背景色设为了nil
Even if you set the background color to nil.
表示不需要背景色
Okay? Which means I don't want a background color.
因为有这个属性 它依旧不会是透明的
It still won't be transparent because of this.
这个opaque不是一项性能优化
This opaque isn't a performance optimization
但却是必要的优化
but it's a hard optimization,
如果设置不正确
meaning it just won't work
它就无法正常工作
if you don't set it to the right thing.
所以如果你想让视图变为透明的
So if you want your view to be transparent
就要把opaque设置为NO
you have to set opaque to no.
同时还要把背景色设为nil
You're also going to want to set your background color to nil
避免填充背景色
so that it's not filling with a background color.
还可以将整个视图变为透明的
It is also possible to make your entire view transparent
用alpha属性
with alpha.
UIView有一个属性叫做alpha
Okay? So UIView has a property called alpha.
如果你将它设为50%
If you set it to 50%
那么视图中全部元素都会透出50%
then everything in your view will be 50% see through.
透明度为50%
Right? 50% transparent.
或者20%等等 看你需要
20% or whatever percent you want.
是整个视图
That's the entire view.
不管里面是什么
No matter what's going on inside.
当然 还有透明颜色
And of course, you have transparent colors
可以用来绘制 填充 描边等等
that you could draw with, fill with, stroke with, whatever.
绘制出来也是透明的
To draw transparently that way as well.
所以有很多方法可以在视图中进行透明绘制
So there's a lot of ways to draw transparently in your view.
如果透明绘制的视图重叠了会怎样呢
What happens if you've draw transparently and views overlap?
它们会互相透过来显示
Well, they show through to each other.
我刚才讲过的
Okay? And I told you that the order
添加子视图的顺序很重要
in which you add the subviews matters.
所有视图都有属性subviews 是一个NSArray
Okay? Every view has a property, an NSArray called subviews.
是视图的列表 顺序很重要
It's the list of views and the order matters.
数组中靠前的视图
The lower one in the array, okay,
比如位置0的视图在后面
the ones that-- like zero are in the back
数组中靠后的视图在前面
and the ones down at the end are in the front.
明白吗
All right?
所以是按照subviews数组中的顺序由后至前
So the subviews array is from back to front.
视图间可以重叠 压在其他视图上面
Okay? And things can overlap and be on top of the others
它们可以透过上面的视图显示出来
and they will show through.
如果中间有一个不透明视图
If you have an opaque on in the middle,
就会遮挡住后面的全部视图
it would block all the ones in the back.
明白吗
See what I mean?
就是这么简单
So it's as simple as that.
实现透明的开销并不少
Now having transparent views is not cheap.
关于性能优化
We talk about performance optimization,
我认为计算机科学的学生
one of the biggest mistakes I think
最容易犯的错误
computer science students make
就是过早优化
is premature optimization.
优化了无关紧要的内容
You're in there optimizing stuff that just doesn't matter.
而这个很重要
This matters.
如果你用了很多透明视图
If you have a lot of transparency,
会占用大量性能资源
it's going to be a performance hit
因为你要根据透明度
because you're talking about having to composite those view
一层层地合成这些视图
on top of each other with alpha.
比直接改变比特值的开销大多了
Way more expensive than just blasting the bits in there.
学过图形学的同学知道我在说什么
Okay? Anyone taking graphics knows that I'm talking about.
所以这是要注意的地方
So this is something you're gonna be a little careful with.
你要将opaque属性设为NO
You're going to set that opaque to no.
明白这里涉及一个性能开销的问题
Understand there's a performance cost there.
这就是我刚说的
Yeah, there's what I am saying.
你还可以隐藏整个视图
You can also hide a view entirely.
可以把它想成是alpha为0的情况
Okay? So it's just like think of it as alpha of zero,
什么都看不到
like you can't see anything.
但是它同时也无法获取任何手势
But it also won't get any gestures.
很像是将视图从视图层级中移除了
It's almost like removing from the view hierarchy,
但是你把它留下了
but you're leaving it,
所以它还在子视图列表中
so it has its space in the subviews list.
还有它的位置 但是并不显示出来
It gets to keep that, but otherwise it doesn't appear.
不进行绘制 无法获取事件
It doesn't draw, it doesn't get events.
就像没在屏幕上一样
It's like it's not even there.
为什么要这样呢
Why do you want that?
因为有时你只是想将某个视图
Well, because sometimes you just want to
暂时从层级中移出
temporarily remove a view from the hierarchy
再把它重新放回来
and put it right back in.
或者过一小段时间后再放回来
So you said-- or put it back in some short time later.
写上hidden=YES
So you say hidden equals yes.
它就不见了
It's gone.
写上hidden=NO 它就重新出现了
You say hidden equals no, oh it reappears.
这比设置为透明更好
Okay? So that's better than setting the transparency.
大部分情况下 UIKit可能会将alpha=0
Although I think mostly the UIKit probably optimizes alpha equals zero
优化为hidden 这是我的猜测
to be the same as hidden as my guess. Okay.
我想作业中可能不需要用到
Probably won't have to do that in homework as my guess.
也可能会用到
But you might.
取决于你的UI的复杂度
Depends on what kind of sophisticated UI you build.
这张幻灯片我就不详细讲了
I'm not going to go through this slide
但是可以想象一下
but you can imagine that
如果你在子程序中
if you're setting up fill colors and clipping
设置了填充颜色 裁剪等等
and all that stuff in a subroutine,
当你从子程序中返回时
when you come back from the subroutine,
这些属性值不变
all those things might still be set.
这样就不好了
And that would be bad.
所以最好能压入和取出你的状态
Okay? So you want to be able to push and pop your state.
也就是保存当前图形上下文
Basically save the current graphics context
然后再恢复它
and then restore it.
也就是这两个函数的功能
And that what these functions do,
CGContextSaveGState和CGContextRestoreGState
CGContextSaveGState and CGContextRestoreGState.
把各种设置都保存起来
We'll save everything,
填充颜色 裁剪区域
all the fill colors and clipping regions.
执行一些操作
You go do a bunch of stuff.
裁剪 填充等等
You know, clip and fill and everything
然后恢复一下 就回到了之前的状态
and then you restore and you're back the way you were.
这样如果你有drawRect方法
So that if you have your drawRect
它调用了这个drawGreenCircle
and it calls this drawGreenCircle thing,
不会在你回到drawRect之后
it won't come back to your drawRect
所有绘制图形都变成绿色
and now everything is drawn in green.
这就是压入和取出状态
Okay? So that's push and pop basically the state.
下面是绘制文本
All right, drawing text.
绘制三角形
Okay, it's all great drawing triangles
填充颜色都可以了
and filling them with colors.
怎样在视图中绘制文本呢
What if you want to draw text inside your view?
当然 绝大多数情况下 在UIKit中
Well, of course we use UILabel to draw
我们使用UILabel绘制文本
the vast majority of text on the screen in UIKit.
但是你可以用NSAttributedString
But you can use NSAttributedString
绘制任意想要的文本
to draw any text you want.
非常简单
And it could not be simpler.
创建属性化字符串
You create the attributes string
添加所需属性
with all the attributes you want.
没有限制 和上次作业中做的
No restrictions, exactly like you learned to do
是一样的
in this last homework assignment
然后只要向那个属性化字符串
and then you just send a message
发送消息drawAtPoint
to that attributed string, drawAtPoint.
这个点
This point.
这个点是一个矩形的左上角
And that will be the upper left corner of a rectangle
矩形包括了全部属性化文本
that includes all that attributed text.
再简单不过了
Okay? It's-- could not be any simpler.
你还可以得到文本大小
You can also find out how big that text is going to take.
文本所占空间大小
How much space that thing is going to take
方法是向属性化字符串发送size
by sending size to the attributed string
它会返回文本空间大小
and it'll tell you how big it is.
你可能会对这部分内容有点困扰
Now you might be a little disturbed by this and like whoa,
属性化字符串并不是UIKit的内容
attributed string is not really a UIKit thing.
它的属性一般都是
All the properties inside usually are,
但它本身并不是
but it itself is not.
是这样的
And that's true.
UIKit实际上是添加了这些方法
UIKit actually adds these methods
drawAtPoint size等
drawAtPoint and size and there's a few other ones.
即便是在完全不同的框架中
It adds them even though
也可以添加方法
it's in a completely different framework
使用了Objective C中的一项机制
using a mechanism in Objective C
可以直接向类中添加方法
where you can add methods to classes
而不用对它们进行子类化
without subclassing them.
叫做Category类别 不好控制
Okay? It's called categories, talk about Wild West.
这就是为什么我要到学期下半部分才讲
That's why I don't show you until the halfway through
因为这项机制可能会被滥用
because it can be abused, this mechanism.
对这部分感到困惑的同学
But that's how this is working
这就是它的工作方式
for those of you who are wondering.
绘制图像差不多是一样的
Drawing images is almost the same.
但是不用NSAttributedString 而是UIImage
But instead of an NSAttributedString, you get a UIImage.
大家知道如何用图像名
So you know how to get one
从图像资产库中得到图像
out of the image assets library with image name.
还可以从文件中创建
There are other ways you can create them from a file.
甚至还可以通过绘至屏外位图
You can even draw into an offscreen bitmap
创建UIImage
to create a UIImage.
有了UIImage之后
Once you have a UIImage in your hand,
只要向它发送drawAtPoint
you just send it drawAtPoint,
就会绘制那幅图像
which will draw that image
左上角位于你所指定的那个点
with its upper left hand corner at the point you specified.
或者用drawInRect 这样会缩放图像
Or drawInRect which will scale the image
以适合你所指定的矩形大小
to fit in the rectangle you specify.
这是通过缩放实现的
Okay? This is a scaling one.
drawAsPatternInRect会平铺图像
Or drawAsPatternInRect which will like tile the image.
重复绘制图像
You know, repeat the image
以填满你指定的矩形
to fill the rectangle that you specified.
还可以得到其他表示法
Okay? And you can get other representations,
绘制内容的PNG表示
PNG representations of things you've drawn
这类的操作
and all these things.
我只是想让大家知道有这个功能
So I just wanted to let you know that's in there.
作业中不需要
You don't need it for your homework but anyway.
所以绘制文本和图像非常简单
So the drawing text and images really easy.
只是用到属性化字符串 UIImage
It's just attributed string and UIImage,
drawAtPoint和drawInRect
drawAtPoint, drawInRect. Okay?
如果bounds变化了会怎样呢
What about when your bounds change? Okay?
当你添加导航栏控制器
You notice when you did the navigation controller
或者选项卡栏控制器时
or the tab bar, you know,
视图的bounds会缩短
your bounds of your view got shrunk down
以适应底部的选项卡栏
to fit the thing at the bottom
或者顶部的导航栏
or fit the thing at the top.
还有在你旋转设备的时候
And also if you rotate your device
显然bounds也会改变
obviously the bounds are going to change.
bounds发生变化了会怎样呢
What happens when your bounds change?
默认情况下 视图的比特值...
Well, by default the bits of your view, the--
最后绘制的内容会被拉伸
that were last draw will get stretched.
并不是我们想要的效果
Okay? Which really is almost never what you want.
大部分内容都希望是被绘制出来的
Okay? I mean most content wants to be drawn
这样分辨率高 看起来比较好看
to get high resolution to look nice.
默认是拉伸 因为这样比重新绘制的
So the default is that because it's way high performance
性能更高
than asking you to draw again.
但是UIView中有一个属性
But there's a property in UIView.
大家需要知道 叫做contentMode
You really want to know called contentMode.
它代表bounds变化时会发生什么
And it says what happens when your bounds change.
底下还有一个UIViewContentModeRedraw
And the one down at the bottom there UIViewContentModeRedraw
如你所想
is doing what you imagine,
是要你在bounds变化时 用drawRect
which is it asks you to redraw your whole view with drawRect
重绘整个视图
whenever your bounds change.
在演示中 我们会设置为重新绘制
Okay? So in our demo we're going to set it to redraw
因为如果卡牌bounds发生变化 我们希望能重绘
because if our cards bounds ever change we want to redraw
这样人头牌面会比较清晰
so we get a nice sharp face card image
右边有小花色符号和文字等等
or the right side little pips on there and text and all that.
你可能也想要这样做
So you might want to do that as well.
UIViewContentModeScaleToFill是默认值
Okay, UIViewContentModeScaleToFill is the default.
绘制内容会被拉伸
That's the bit stretcher.
以上是绘制部分的内容
Okay, so that's the drawing side of things.
我们来讲一下输入部分
Now let's talk about the input side.
手势识别
Okay, the recognizing gestures.
手指触摸屏幕的原始数据
It is possible to get the raw data
是可以得到的
about fingers touching the screen.
触摸的数量 手指的位置和移动
How many they're touching, where the fingers are, when they move.
以前
But-- and it used to be that
真的需要自己查看这些数据
you actually had to look at all that data
判断用户在做什么
to figure out what the heck the user was doing.
滑动还是捏合
Swiping or pinching?
真是个噩梦
It was a nightmare.
无法相信有人真的这样做了
I mean I can't believe people actually did it.
代码非常难懂
It was quite esoteric code.
最近发布的几个iOS版本解决了这个问题
But the last few iOS releases have had the right way to do it
添加了手势识别器功能
which is gesture recognizers. Okay?
所以我们理解用户操作的方法是
So the way we're gonna understand what the user is doing is
系统会替我们识别特定手势
this system is gonna recognize certain gestures for us
在手势发生时告诉我们
and tell us when those gestures are happening.
显然我们想要用这种方式
Okay? Obviously you want to do this.
有一个类
The class that is the base
是这些手势识别的基础
for all these recognizing gestures
叫做UIGestureRecognizer
is called UIGestureRecognizer.
它是一个抽象类
It's an abstract class.
不允许对它进行实例化
Okay, you never instantiate it.
但它有很多具体子类
But it has a lot of concrete subclasses
比如捏合手势 点击手势等
like pinch gesture, tap gesture, all that.
这些具体子类
And those are the things
能够真正识别手势
that does the actual recognition of a gesture
并在手势发生时与你通信
and communicating with you when it does.
使用手势识别器有两步
There's two parts to using a gesture recognizer.
先要创建手势识别器 添加到视图中
You have to create a gesture recognizer and add it to a view.
只能将识别器添加到视图中
You can only add a recognizer to a view.
因为只有视图具有坐标系
Because views are the only ones that have a coordinate system
能够知道触发手势的
to know where the touches were
触摸的位置
that cause the gesture to happen.
第二步是你需要提供一个处理器
And then number two is you've got to provide the handler,
当手势发生时要调用的一个方法
a method to call when the gesture happens
或者是手势正在发生时
or is happening.
如果是捏合手势
If it's like a pinch it's, you know,
手势处理器会随着来回缩放
that gesture handle is going to get called a lot
多次被调用
as the pinch goes out and in.
拖动手势也是这样
Or if it's a pan.
但如果是滑动或点击
Okay? But if it's a swipe or a tap
就只会调用一次
you're just going to get called once.
明白吗
Make sense?
这就是需要做的两步操作
So those are the two things that you need to do.
第一步一般由控制器完成
Usually number one is done by controller,
但有时是视图自己完成
although it's sometimes views do it to themselves
为自己添加一个手势识别器
where they add a gesture recognizer to themselves.
而步骤二通常由视图提供
And number two is often provided by the view.
也就是说 处理器
In other words the handler,
手势发生时或发生后要做的事情
the thing to do when the gesture is happening or happened,
很多时候 是视图实现了那个方法
a lot of times the view implements that method.
所以即便可能是由控制器
So even though the controller
向视图添加了手势识别器
might add the gesture recognizer to the view,
当它添加时 它会告诉系统
when it adds it, it tells the system
如果你识别出手势 让视图来处理
and when you recognize the gesture, let the view handle it.
但是控制器可以自行处理
But the controller can handle it itself.
两种方式我们都会演示
So we'll do both in the demo.
让控制器来处理
We'll have the controller handle it.
和让视图来处理
We'll have the view handle it.
都演示一下
The whole deal.
我们来看一下代码
So let's take a look at the code.
向视图添加手势识别器的
What the code would look like
代码是怎样的
to add a gesture recognizer to a view.
在控制器中向视图添加手势识别器
A gesture recognizer to a view in a controller.
所以这段示例代码是在控制器中的
So this code that I'm trying right here is in a controller.
它是视图输出口panableView的setter
It's the setter of an outlet for a view called pannableView.
输出口叫做pannableView
Okay? That's the name of the outlet, pannableView.
按住control键进行拖动
So this would just control drag.
连接起来就创建了输出口
Wire it up and now as an outlet
这是输出口的setter
and now we're in the setter.
而在setter中要做的是
And in the setter what we're going to do is
当控制器中的视图设好以后
when that view is set in our controller,
我们要向那个视图添加手势识别器
we're going to add a gesture recognizer to that view.
这样视图就可以识别拖动手势了
So that that view starts recognizing the pan gesture.
拖动是指用手指触摸着屏幕来回移动
Pan is put your finger down and move around.
这叫拖动
That's called panning.
非常简单
So it's very simple.
可以看到
You can see that
我们创建了一个UIGestureRecognizer的具体子类
we create a concrete subclass of gesture recognizer
叫做UIPanGestureRecognizer
called UIPanGestureRecognizer.
就是黄色气泡显示的那条代码
You see that there in the yellow bubble.
可以看到创建时的指定初始化方法
And when we create it you can see its designated initializer.
所有实体类的指定初始化方法
All the concrete classes' designate initializer
都需要两个参数
take two arguments.
一个是target目标
One is the target.
也就是手势发生时 谁来处理
That's who's going to handle this gesture when it happens.
第二个参数是该对象中要调用的方法
And the second thing is the method to call in that object.
所以这里pan要被发送到那个视图
So here pan is going to be sent to the view itself.
也就是我们要为其添加手势识别器的
The same view that we're gonna
那个视图
add this gesture recognizer to.
下面一步就只要
And then we just do the step
将手势识别器添加到视图
of adding the gesture recognizer to the view.
addGestureRecognizer方法
The method addGestureRecognizer
只能由UIView实现
is only implemented by UIView.
控制器无法识别手势
So a controller can't recognize a gesture.
它没有坐标系 任何方法都无法完成
It was no coordinate system to do that in any way.
所以某些视图需要处理手势
So some view has to be handling this gesture
当然可以用self.view识别手势
and yes you can have self.view recognize gestures.
用整个视图
Right? The whole view.
完全没问题
That's perfectly fine.
操作中的目标target可以是控制器
And yes, the target in action could be the controller.
控制器中的方法
A method in the controller.
不一定是视图
It doesn't have to be a view.
可以是任意对象
Okay? That can be any object.
那我们如何实现目标呢 那个拖动调用
So how do we implement that target, that pan calling. Right?
我在拖动 在捏合
So I'm panning, I'm pinching
在拖动时发送拖动调用
and I'm getting sent pan calling when I'm panning.
我要在那个方法中做什么呢
What do I do inside that method?
答案是 UIGestureRecognizer的所有具体子类
And the answer is that each concrete subclass
都会提供一些方法来辅助你
of UIGestureRecognizer will provide some methods to help you.
例如 UIPanGestureRecognizer
Okay? So for example the pan gesture recognizer
提供这三个方法
provides these three methods.
translationInView代表触摸移动距离
TranslationInView, that's how far the touch moved
从上次重置之后的移动距离
since it's-- since basically it was last reset.
手指触摸到屏幕时 系统进行重置
Okay? It starts off reset when the touch goes down.
在移动过程中 你可以重置
So as you move unless you reset it
可以在识别器中实现
which you can do in your recognizer.
稍后会演示
We'll show you that.
这个方法会告诉你从起点开始的
It's going to tell you the cumulative translation distance
累计移动距离
from where you started.
这就是translationView
Okay? So that's translationView.
velocityInView代表移动速度
velocityInView is how fast it's moving.
手指移动速度是不是很快
Is your finger moving quickly
好像滑动之类的
like it's almost like a swipe or something?
还是移动得很慢
Or is it moving really slow?
用户是想做些精细操作吗
Is the user trying to really do some detail work?
这个方法可以提供速度信息
So this is telling the velocity.
最后一个setTranslation inView
And then setTranslation inView
允许你对移动距离进行重置
allows you to reset the translation.
我刚才讲了
Okay? Because I told you
translationInView代表上次重置之后的距离
translationInView is since the last reset.
setTranslation可以将其重置至某点
SetTranslation will let you to reset it to some point.
然后下次拖动被调用时
And then the next pan calling in you get,
下次手指移动时
the next finger movement,
移动距离就会是
the translation will be
从重置的那个点到最后位置的距离
from the place you just reset to the last time.
这就是UIPanGestureRecognizer提供的方法
So those are given to you by pan gesture recognizer
你还继承了...
and you also inherit --
UIPanGestureRecognizer还从UIGestureRecognizer
pan gesture also inherits a very important property
从这个抽象超类继承了一个非常重要的属性
from UIGestureRecognizer, the abstract superclass
叫做state状态
called state.
状态有很多种不同的情况
Now state can be a lot of different things.
这里是比较有趣的几个状态
Here are some of the more interesting ones.
UIGestureRecognizerStateBegan表示
UIGestureRecognizerStateBegan means
这是一个连续运动的手势
this is a continuous motion kind of thing
比如拖动或捏合
like a pan or a pinch
而它刚刚开始
and it just started.
手指刚触碰到屏幕
Finger just went down.
UIGestureRecognizerStateChanged表示
Okay? Then UIGestureRecognizerStateChanged means
这是一个连续运动手势 并且它变化了
it's one of those continuous things and it changed.
手指移动了
The fingers moved.
Changed代表手指移动了
Okay? Changed means it moved.
还有UIGestureRecognizerStateEnded
And then there's UIGestureRecognizerStateEnded.
手指抬离屏幕了
Finger went up.
和大家可能想到的一样
Okay? Exactly what you would think.
还有其他的状态 比如
But there's other states like UIGestureRecognizerState--
UIGestureRecognizerStateRecognized
what's it called-- recognized.
它出现于不连续手势的情况
Okay? That one you get for discrete gestures
比如点击或滑动
like taps or swipes.
你不会得到Began Changed Ended状态
You don't get all this began, moved or began changed ended.
只会得到Recognized
You just get recognized.
我识别出了滑动
I recognize the swipe.
我识别出了点击
I recognize the tap.
明白吗 有几种不同的状态
You see? So different state there.
所以连续手势是得不到Recognized的
So recognized you'll never get on the continuous ones.
可能会得到
Well, you might get it,
但是不会太在意它
but you wouldn't pay much attention to it.
但是不连续手势中就是要看这个状态
But on the discrete ones that's what you look at,
连续手势对应的是Began Changed Ended
vice versa with the began, changed, ended.
还可以得到Cancelled和Failed
You can also get cancelled and failed,
这类状态
things like that.
它们出现的情况是
These happen when things like
你正在做手势时
you're in the middle of a gesture
有电话打进来了
and a phone call comes in.
这时手势就断掉了
Okay? Boom, that gesture just got blown out of the water.
所以好的代码都会注意Failed和Canceled
So really good code will pay attention to failed and canceled
确保当手势中断时
and make sure these things aren't in a wacky state
它们的状态正常
if the thing gets aborted right in the middle.
我就不演示了
So I'm not going to show that in the demo
因为时间很紧张
because time is gonna be of the essence here.
大家可以查看相关文档
But you can look at the documentation
学习如何处理这些状态
on how to handle those.
好了
All right.
这些具体子类
So what would pan look like
为我们提供了这些方法
given that we have those methods
那么pan方法是如何实现的呢
that the concrete things provides?
当手指刚放到屏幕上的时候
So I'm probably not going to do anything
我可能不会做任何操作
when the finger first goes down
因为还没有发生任何实际的变化
because nothing has really changed yet.
但只要手指开始移动
But as soon as it starts changing
或者离开屏幕
or when the finger goes back up
我就要根据新位置的不同
I'm then going to update something inside my view
更新视图内的某些内容
based on where this new position is.
而获取新位置的方法
And I'm going to get that new position
就是向recognizer这个UIPanGestureRecognizer请求
by asking the recognizer, the pan gesture recognizer
在当前视图中的移动距离
what's the translation in the view self.
在获取移动距离时
Okay? The reason we specify the view
指定视图
when we say the translation
是因为我们需要坐标系
is because we need a coordinate system.
我们需要知道
Okay? We got to know what coordinate system
是在哪个坐标系中移动的
we're talking about this translation being.
所以在这个例子中是self
All right. So self in this case,
因为拖动调用发生在视图中
because pan calling is in the view.
我可能会设置原点或者某些属性
Like I might set my origin or some property.
这行示例代码
This is just an example line of code
就是假设我有一幅图之类的
if I had a graph of something like that.
或许会移动这幅图
Maybe moving the graph around.
就是不断重置原点
It's just constantly resetting the origin.
既然我在移动原点时
And here since I'm moving the origin
是将原点从调用时所在位置
from where it exists at the time this is called
按照移动距离进行移动
by some little translation
我希望每次都重置移动距离
I want to reset that translation every time.
这样就总能得到小的移动距离增量
So that I'm always getting little incremental translation movements
一点点地移动原点
and I'm moving my origin around incrementally.
否则我还得记着原点最初的位置
Otherwise I'd have to keep track of where did my origin start,
然后每次调用这个方法时
and then every time this was called
还要找出不同 然后再移动
I'd have to find the difference and then move it .
用这里的这种方法 我就不用担心了
This way I don't have to worry about it.
我只要不断将距离重置为零
I just keep resetting the thing back to zero
这样就会不断得到较小的移动距离
and so I keep getting these tiny changes.
随时将其应用到视图中
I just keep applying them to my view.
连续手势采用这种模式是很常见的
This's very common pattern to do this for these continuous ones.
不断重置
Constantly resetting.
我们会在演示中实现
We'll do that in our demo.
我们要实现的是缩放 但同样是通过重置的方法
We're going to do pinch but we'll do the same resetting.
我们再看看其他具体识别类
Okay, so let's look at some of the other concrete recognizers.
Pinch捏合 它没有移动距离属性
Pinch. Okay, pinch doesn't have translation,
它有一个缩放比例属性scale
it has a scale.
捏合手势刚开始时 缩放比例为1.0
So when the pinch first starts, the scale is one, 1.0.
随着逐渐放大 比例变为1.1 1.2 1.5 2.0
And as I go out 1.1, 1.2, 1.5, 2.0.
随着缩小又变为1.5, 1.2, 1.0, 0.9, 0.8, 0.7, 0.6
1.5, 1.2, 1.0, 0.9, 0.8, 0.7, 0.6.
明白吗
Okay? That make sense?
就是这样变化的
So, that's what is happening there.
速度velocity指的是比例系数的变化速度
And then, the velocity is how fast in scale factor change,
每秒钟变化多少
per second that's happening.
你是在快速缩小呢
So, are you pinching really fast in,
还是在快速放大 等等
pinching fast out, etcetera?
这可以告诉你某些迹象
So, that's giving you, again, some indication,
用户在做什么
what's the user--
如果他们迅速反复放大
if they're pinching out really quickly, repeatedly,
也许他们是想要快速放大
maybe they're trying to really zoom out fast,
你可以用更快的速度放大之类的
you can zoom out faster than usual or something.
旋转手势识别 也是两指手势
Rotation Gesture Recognizer, also a two-finger thing,
和捏合很像 但是会旋转手指
like a pinch, except for you turn your fingers.
它会通过弧度告诉你旋转的信息
And it's going to tell you the rotation in radians.
大家都知道什么是弧度吧
Everyone know what radians are, right?
一圈对应的弧度是0到2π
Zero to 2 pi around a circle, in radians.
如果不知道就去查一下
Look it up if you don't know it.
它也有速度属性 告诉你每秒的变化弧度
And that's also telling you velocity in radians per second,
用户旋转的速度是怎样的
how fast they're-- the person're rotating.
滑动手势是不连续手势之一
Swipe Gesture is one of these discrete gestures.
你只要设好这个滑动手势
You just set up this Swipe Gesture,
使用alloc/init设好目标和操作
you alloc and init with the target and the action,
然后设置好方向direction属性
and then you set these properties' direction
或者所需触控数量numberOfTouchesRequired属性
or numberOfTouchesRequired.
触控数量的意思是
Number of touches means
这个滑动手势需要两根手指还是一根手指来完成
this is a swipe with two fingers or one finger.
这就是触控数量的意思 两指 一指
That's what number of touches means, two finger, one finger,
三指 五指 按你的需要设置
three finger, five fingers, whatever you want,
方向是从左到右 从右到左
and the direction is left to right, right to left,
从上到下 从下到上
top to bottom, or bottom to top.
你创建好之后
Okay? So, you create it
如果出现了滑动手势
and then if a swipe happens
符合你的条件 你就会得到...
that meets all that, you'll get the --
你的处理器就会被调用一次 传递状态为Recognized
your handler called once with "Recognized" as the state.
明白吗
That make sense?
滑动手势并不需要追踪
So, swipe is something you don't track,
它直接告诉你 我发现了一个滑动手势
it just tells you, "Oh, I saw a swipe."
而且它很聪明
And, yes, it's smart about--
如果你同时有拖动手势识别器
if you have a Pan Gesture Recognizer
和滑动手势识别
and a Swipe Gesture Recognizer,
如果你非常顺畅地进行滑动
if you swipe smoothly enough,
系统就会判断手势为滑动
it will see it as a swipe.
但是如果你移动得很慢
But if you go slower, or you don't go, you know--
或者走的是斜线等等
you're going in a diagonal or something like that,
系统就会认为手势是拖动
it will say, "Oh, no, that's a pan."
所以系统知道
Okay, so it knows how to kind of
如何辨别手势的不同之处
tell the difference between gestures.
越多越好
Okay? As much as possible.
非常好用
It's pretty cool.
点击手势和滑动手势是一样的
Tap Gesture, just like Swipe Gesture.
是不连续手势
It's discrete.
你先设置好
You set it up,
点击几下 双击还是单击
how many taps, double tap, single tap,
用几根手指等等
how many fingers, etcetera.
发现手势后 它会向你发送Recognized
And it will send you "Recognized" when it sees it.
滑动手势识别器可以识别对角线滑动吗
Can you do Swipe Gesture Recognizer for corners or no?
只有那四个方向吗
Is it only those four directions?
问题是 滑动手势是否可以
The question is, can you do Swipe Gestures like,
斜着滑向四角 而不是水平滑动
you mean, like swiping up into a corner, as opposed to...
是的
Right .
我觉得不能
I don't think so.
我认为只有上下左右四个方向
I think it's just left-right, up and down.
我可能说的不对
I could be wrong about that.
我有一段时间没看文档了
I haven't looked in the documentation for a while,
但是我认为只有那四种方向
but I think it's only those four.
好了 我们来演示
All right, so let's do the demo.
演示呢
Okay? So, it's going to be--
我会快速演示一遍
I'm going to go fast,
需要演示的内容很多
there's a lot to show you here, okay?
但我只准备演示
But I'm only going to show you
今天讲过的全部内容
all the things we just talked about today.
我准备用一个综合示例
But I'm going to try to show all of it to you
尽量演示全部内容
in a comprehensive demo.
我先讲讲下面的安排
Let me talk about what's coming up
这样我们演示完就可以直接下课了
so that we can just finish the demo and be done.
同样 我们希望周五的时候
Again, we're hoping on Friday
能正常运行大学开发者计划
to get this university developer program thing going,
但是似乎还是不能用
but it looks like that's still not working.
明天会在Piazza上通知周五是否取消
Watch Piazza tomorrow for whether Friday is canceled.
现在看起来不乐观
At this point, it's not looking good.
这是只适用于斯坦福大学的
That would be a Stanford-only thing, anyway.
作业期限是从周一开始的一个星期
The homework, as I said, is due a week from Monday.
从今天开始的话 超过七天
So, more than seven days from now,
是周一之后的一个星期
a week from Monday.
我强烈建议大家马上开始做
I really strongly recommend you get started
先完成自定义视图
on the part that is a custom view
和手势识别器的部分
and gesture recognizer immediately.
不要等到下周二或周三
Do not wait until next Tuesday or Wednesday,
因为到了那个时候你就会发现
because then you're going to find that
想要一周内赶完这个作业
this is a lot of work for this assignment
工作量很大
to try and jam into one week.
所以我才给大家
That's why I've given you, you know, whatever--
留了这么多天
however many days it is.
这部分
Do this part--
如果可以 最好在周一前做完
I would try and do this part before next Monday if you can,
当然越早越好
but certainly do this part as soon as possible.
剩下的部分
Then, the rest of the part,
动画和自动布局
which is animation and autolayout,
我会在下周一
which I'll be talking about on Monday
或者下周三讲到
and maybe next Wednesday,
可以完成这部分之后 再完成那一部分
you can leave that-- you can do that after you do this part.
它们之间的关联并不紧密
They're not so intertwined that it's like, oh,
不要求同时完成
you've got to do them all at the same time.
可以有先后顺序
It's something that you can do after.
好了
Okey dokey.
我们要在Xcode中新建一个项目
So, we are going to create a new project in Xcode here.
我要叫它...
And, I'm going to call that--
这些开始设置我就快速带过了
I'm going fast through a lot of these starting up things,
大家都已经知道怎么做了
because you know how to do this already.
我要叫它SuperCard
So, I'm going to call this one SuperCard.
这里有趣的一点是
One thing interesting here,
我不指定类前缀
I'm not going to specify a class prefix,
大家可以看一下是什么样的
just so you see what that looks like,
我们之前总是指定类前缀
because we've always specified that,
比如CardGame等
like CardGame or something like that.
这里我就不指定了 我们再看看
So, I'm just going to not specify that, and we'll see.
保存在主目录Developer下
I'm going to create it in my home directory Developer
和往常一样
as I usually do.
可以看这里
Here, you can go and see right here
列着ViewController.h和ViewController.m
where it says ViewController.h and ViewController.m,
这是我的视图控制器类的名字
that's the name of my view controller classes,
这种名字真的很糟糕
which is really-- those are bad names.
这也就是为什么我们通常都要添加类前缀
And that's why we usually want to put something
比如CardGameViewController
in that class prefix, like CardGameViewController.
我要把这些移走
Okay? I'm going to move these down out of the way.
这边这是我的视图 storyboard视图
Otherwise, here's my view, right, my storyboard view.
可以在这边打开它的控制器
And I could bring up the controller for it right here.
可以看到 系统自动添加了viewDidLoad方法
You can see I've got a viewDidLoad,
我会留下
which I'll go ahead and leave.
内存警告方法不需要 删掉
Memory warning, don't need that.
我只要在这个视图中做一件事
Okay. And all I'm going to do in this view--
我们把它变小点
let's make this a little smaller--
就是添加一个自定义视图
is put a single view, custom view,
是一张扑克牌
which is going to be a playing card
一张真正的扑克牌 绘制出来的牌
but a real playing card, drawn playing card. Okay?
我们先从我们总爱做的事情入手
So, let's start by doing what we always love to do,
也就是将背景设为苔藓色
but which is setting our background here to moss.
我爱苔藓色 在这
I love moss. There it is.
背景变为了苔藓色
Okay, there's our moss.
我们喜欢这样
We like that.
我这样做主要是为了能让大家看得更清楚
I'm doing that mostly so you can see what's going on better.
然后我要从这里拖出自定义视图
And, then I'm going to grab this custom view out of here.
在列表下面
So, let's go down here.
UIView位置很靠下 在下半部分 在这
UIView is pretty far down, past halfway. There it is.
看这里写的
See right here,
视图代表一个矩形区域
"View represents a rectangular region
在其内绘制和接收事件
which draws and receive events."
只要将它拖出来 放到这里
And you just drag it out and put it out here.
我不想要它这么大
I don't want it to be this big,
所以我要把它缩小一点
so I'm going to make it smaller.
它的大小究竟是多少并不重要
It really doesn't matter exactly what size I make this,
因为我要让我的绘制类
because I'm going to make my class, my drawing class,
在任意尺寸下都可以正常绘制
so that it'll draw properly in pretty much any size.
但如果不是常规比例就不好看了
Now, it's going to look pretty bad if it's not--
通常是高大于宽
you know, mostly tall than wide,
如果扑克牌又宽又短
because playing cards don't look very good
看起来也不太好看
if they're wide and short.
视图可以正常运行
Okay? My view will work, it won't--
但用户会认不太出来它是一张牌
people won't recognize it very much as a card,
但是当然没问题
but it certainly would be fine.
在作业中
And in your assignment,
大家创建自定义视图时
the custom view you're going to create,
也要这样做
you also want to make it that way
这样它就可以正常运行于任意大小的bounds
so that it works in any size bounds.
在作业中
And in that card,
要实现的是Set卡牌
since it's gonna be a set card for you,
Set卡牌实际上可以是横向的
set cards actually could make sense being sideways.
卡牌上的三个符号最好是横向排列
You would want the three symbols, you know,
而不是竖向排列
going sideways instead of up and down.
一个好的解决办法
So, a good solution would make, really,
会让Set卡牌在任意纵横比下都很好看
any aspect ratio look nice for a set card.
但是扑克牌
But playing cards
大多只有竖向时才好看
mostly only going to look good kind of set up.
接下来
So, what we do here then
我们转到标识符检查器
is we go to this identity inspector,
在这里设置这个视图的类
and here we want to set our class of this view
将其设为某个自定义类
to be some custom class, right?
目前它只是一个通用的UIView
Right now, it's just a generic UIView,
那我们来创建那个类
and so let's go create that class.
选择新建文件
So, I'm just going to do File, New File,
和之前新建类一样
just like we always do to create a class.
选择Objective-C类
Objective-C.
它会是UIView的子类
This one's going to be a subclass of UIView,
而不是UIViewController等的子类
okay, instead of UIViewController or anything else.
我要叫它PlayingCardView
I'm going to call it PlayingCardView.
它会是一个
Okay, this is going to be
通用扑克牌显示视图
a generic playing card displaying view.
完全通用
Completely generic,
不和Machismo模型绑定
not tied to the Machismo model,
也不和其他东西绑定
not tied to anything else.
就像是独立的
It's just like standalone.
要记住 创建视图时
And remember that when we create views,
进入视图阵营的东西
things that go in the view camp,
通用性越强越好
they want to be as generic as possible
可重用性越强越好
and reusable as possible,
这样这个PlayingCardView
so that I could use this PlayingCardView
在扑克牌游戏和Machismo中都可以使用
in my poker game app and also in Machismo.
这也就是为什么
Okay? That's why--
我们强调使用
we really want to try and enforce
它的通用性
that kind of generic nature of it.
这是PlayingCardView的实现文件
So, here's PlayingCardView's implementation.
可以看到这里有intiWithFrame方法
You can see that I've got intiWithFrame right here,
这是它的指定初始化方法
that's its designated initializer.
还可以看到我把这个非常重要的drawRect方法
And you can see I've got the all-important drawRect
注释掉了
commented out.
如果你不注释掉
If you don't comment--
如果你把它注释掉
if you comment this out,
不添加任何内容
and you don't put anything in there,
就会占用大量性能资源
that's going to give you a performance hit,
因为系统会认为
because it's going to think
这个视图需要不断重绘
this view needs to be redrawn all the time,
但其实它不需要
when in fact it doesn't.
所以我们要先把它注释掉
So, that's why it starts out commented out,
但是我们要在这里绘制
but we are going to draw in here,
所以会再取消注释
so we will be uncommented it out.
我要把这个方法移动一下
I'm going to move this--
我们要在方法中添加某些操作
we're going to do something in there,
但我要把它先移开 放到下面来
but I'm going to move it down, out of the way,
合适的时候再来实现
because we're going to do that at the appropriate time.
每次新建类
Okay, so any time we create a new class,
需要考虑的很重要的一点就是公有API
really important to think about is public APIs,
我们来做一下
so let's do that.
看一下它的公有API
Let's look at its public API.
它是个视图 对吧
It's a view, right?
它需要做什么
What does it need to do?
这个PlayingCard需要显示...
Well, this playing card needs to display--
PlayingCardView需要显示扑克牌
PlayingCardView needs to display a playing card,
所以我们最好能够指定要哪张牌
so we better have some way of specifying which card we want.
有些人可能会认为
Now, some of you might say,
太棒了 我们用Card
"Oh, great. Let's use Card star."
或者PlayingCard *也不错
or, "PlayingCard star would be great
PlayingCard *包含了所有我们需要的内容
because PlayingCard star has got everything we need."
但是我说过了 我不想
But, again, I don't want to
将这个通用可重用视图和那个模型绑定
tie this generic reusable view to that model.
所以我要用NSUInteger rank
So instead, I'm going to have NSUInteger rank,
还有NSString *suit
and I'm going to have NSString suit,
我还要再加一个
and I'm also going to have something
在另外一个模型中甚至没有它
that's not even in that other model,
是nonatomic的 BOOL faceUp
which is nonatomic BOOL faceUp.
添加这个属性
Okay? I'm going to have it
用来记录卡牌是否正面朝上
so my card is either face up or face down.
这是一个扑克牌视图
This is a playing card view,
它要能显示牌面向上或向下的扑克牌
it's got to be able to display the card in either up or down.
这就是我的API 我就需要这些
So, that's my API. That's all I really need.
现在我们只要在实现文件中
And so we've just got to implement that API
实现API
in our implementation.
我先要做一件事 就是这个
One thing I'm going to do right off the bat is this.
看到了吗 我一下就把这些都打出来了
Okay? Now, I typed this really fast.
就这样
That was it.
这里做的是在所有公有API的setter中
All I'm doing here is all the setters for all my public API,
调用setNeedsDisplay
I am calling setNeedsDisplay.
因为如果有人修改了suit 或者...
Okay? Because if someone changes the suit, or the--
这里我可以写上
and yes, I could say,
if _suit!=suit
if underbar suit does not equal suit,
就保存自己 然后setNeedsDisplay
then save myself and setNeedsDisplay,
但这里只是演示一下
but-- okay, demo time here.
用setNeedsDisplay只是为了确保
So I'm doing setNeedsDisplay just to make sure,
如果有人修改了rank或者suit
if anyone changes the rank or the suit
或者牌面朝向
or the faceUp-ness of my thing,
我就告诉系统我需要被重绘
I tell the system I need to be redrawn.
明白吗 我为什么这么做
Do you understand this, why I do that?
好极了
Okay, excellent.
我们来实现drawRect
So, let's dive into drawRect here.
取消它的注释
I'm going to uncomment it out,
在这里开始绘制
okay, and start drawing here.
如果我没有...
Now, if I'm not--
我全部都会用UIBezierPath来实现
I'm going to do all my stuff with UIBezierPath, so--
不了 我会用一次context
well, actually, no, I'll do a context here,
演示一下上下文的用法
just to show you the context.
我们稍后再用它
We'll do it a little later,
先用UIBezierPath
but we're going to start off doing UIBezierPath,
我们先设置扑克牌的外观
and let's start with the outside of my card
我想要圆角矩形的
which I want to be a rounded rect, right?
我想让扑克牌是圆角矩形的
I want my cards to be a rounded rect.
我只要在这里创建一个贝赛尔曲线 UIBezierPath
So, I'm just gonna create a Bezier path here, UIBezierPath.
我要叫它...
I'm going to call it--
把其他面板隐藏起来
and let me make some more space,
方便大家看到更多代码
so we can see lots of code here.
我要叫它roundedRect
RoundedRect, I'll call it.
我要用UIBezierPath
And I do that with UIBezier--
实际上有一个类方法可以实现
actually there's a class method that does that,
bezierPathWithRoundedRect 下面这个
bezierPath for RoundedRects, down here, this one.
我要让这个圆角矩形
And I'm going to have that rounded rect
越大越好
be as big as possible,
所以我指定self.bounds
so I specify self.bounds
为绘制roundedRect的矩形
as the rectangle to draw this roundedRect in.
self.bounds是我的坐标系
Okay? Self.bounds is my coordinate system.
它的宽度和高度组成的空间
Its width and height is the amount of space
就是我在屏幕上用来绘制的范围
I have onscreen to draw in.
cornerRadius呢
Okay, cornerRadius,
我要在这里添加一段神奇的代码
I'm going to throw in some magic code here for that.
这很重要
This is an important thing.
cornerRadius代表圆角矩形的
This cornerRadius is how many points is in the radius
圆角的半径有多少个点
as it goes around the corner of the rounded rect.
它的值取决于卡牌的大小
And, really, that number depends on how big my card is.
如果卡牌很大 半径就要很大
If I have a big card, I want a big radius,
如果卡牌很小 半径就要很小
if I have a really small card, I want a really small radius.
所以我创建了这个cornerScaleFactor
So, I've created this cornerScaleFactor,
定义了高度的标准值
which I've just standardized to some height,
可以研究一下这些数字
and I can play with these numbers
找到适用于全部尺寸的数值
to see what works for all sizes.
然后选择一个半径值
And then, I'm going to pick a radius
这个高度对应的半径是12
that at this height is 12,
用起来很不错
and that works pretty nicely, right?
然后对它进行等比缩放
And then, I'm going to scale it.
我要在这里调用这个方法
Okay? So I'm going to call this method right here,
cornerRadius
cornerRadius, corner radius.
你会看到
And you'll see
我还会在其他地方用到比例系数
I'm gonna use that scale factor in other places, too,
用来进行放大
to try and scale it up.
这就是我说过的
And this is part of what I'm talking about,
你需要实现在任意bounds下
you need this thing to draw
都能正常进行绘制
in any size bounds to make sense.
所以你需要这些内容
So, you're gonna have to have a little bit of stuff
根据目标的大小
that is dependent on, you know, the size and height of this thing
选择合适尺寸的圆角矩形等
to pick the right size rounded rects and things like that.
对于这个roundedRect
So, the first thing that
我先要做的是
I'm gonna do to this roundedRect actually,
进行裁剪
is I'm gonna clip to it,
抱歉 是addClip
because I don't-- sorry addClip.
我要...
I'm going to--
我并不想在roundedRect之外绘图
I don't ever want to draw outside that roundedRect.
它是我的卡牌的内部绘制区
Okay? That's the interior of my card,
所以我要用它进行裁剪
so I'm just going to clip to that.
还可以这样做
It also lets me do something like this.
UIColor whiteColor 设置为填充色
UIColor whiteColor, set my fill color,
然后我可以...
and then I can just--
抱歉 多打了个括号
Sorry, I do that a lot.
然后我只要用这个C函数
Then, I'm just going to use this C function,
因为我想演示它的用法
because I just want to show this to you.
UIRectFil 然后指定一个矩形self.bounds
UIRectFill, and you specify a rectangle, self.bounds.
这样就填充了这个矩形
Okay, this just fills this rectangle.
这就像是创建路径
So, it's kind of like shorthand for creating that path,
填充等等的简化版本
filling it and all that stuff.
它直接就填充了 很好用的UIKit的内容
It just fills it, this nice little UIKit thing.
它会创建一个大矩形
And this is going to make a big rectangle,
这个裁剪区域会让roundedRect的内部
but this clip is going to keep the white of this
是白色的
on the inside of that roundedRect.
所以不会绘制四角的白色区域
So it's not going to draw the white in the corners up there.
但是这里有个问题
However, I've got a problem here,
这个视图的背景色默认为白色
in that my background color for this view is by default white,
所以这些操作都位于一个大的白色矩形中
so it's doing this all on a big white rectangle
包括那四个角
that includes those corners.
所以背景色不能是白色了
So, I need to stop my background from being white,
我还需要告诉系统
and I also need to tell the system
我的扑克牌是透明的
that my playing card is not opaque.
我要在initWithFrame中实现
Okay? So, I'm gonna do that in initWithFrame down here,
但我要用正确的方法来实现
but I'm going to do it in the right way,
添加一个setup方法
which is to have a setup method.
在setup中 我要将背景色设为nil
And in setup, I'm going to set my background color to nil,
表示不要绘制背景
which means that I don't-- don't draw a background for me,
将opaque设为NO 是透明的
and I'm going to set opaque to no, I'm not opaque.
我还要加上
I'm also going to do
contentMode=UIViewContentModeRedraw
that contentMode equals UIViewContentModeRedraw.
还记得吗 我说了如果bounds变化了
Remember I told you that if my bounds ever change,
我就要调用drawRect
I want to get my drawRect called.
在这个示例中 bounds不会发生变化
Now, my bounds is not gonna change in this demo,
但我知道如果它变化了 我需要这样做
but I know that if it ever does, that's what I want.
然后 很重要的一点是
And then, really importantly,
我要在awakeFromNib中执行它
I want to make sure I do this in awakeFromNib.
self setup
Okay, self setup.
因为实际上 在这个示例中
Because, in fact, in this demo,
我要从storyboard中创建视图
I am going to be creating this view in a storyboard.
而不用alloc/init
I'm not doing alloc init on it,
所以我要用这种方法来做准备
so this is how I'm going to get set up.
有什么问题
Okay? Question.
将背景色设为nil 而不用UIColor clearColor
What's the advantage of setting background color to nil,
有什么优点吗
instead of UIColor clearColor?
问题是
Yeah, so the question is,
这里用nil 而不用UIColor clearColor
What's the advantage here of saying nil
有什么优点
versus UIColor clearColor?
答案是没有什么优点
And the answer is there's no advantage,
除了用nil能比较直观地表达我的意思
except for that, really, what I intend here is
就是没有背景色
I don't have a background color.
你们可以不这样用
So you can argue--
只是风格不同
It's just a style thing,
两种方式没有什么不同
but there's no difference in there.
这样我们就准备好了
Okay? So, now we're nice and set up.
还要快速讲一个东西
Oh, one thing I'm going to show you real quick here
#pragma
is pound sign pragma.
大家知不知道它
I don't know if you guys know about that.
有多少人知道#pragma是什么意思
How many people know what pound sign pragma is?
几乎没人知道 很好
Okay, almost nobody. This is awesome, then.
如果加一个mark 变为pragma mark
Okay, so if you do a mark, a pragma mark,
你可以加一段注释
you can put a little comment
比如Initialization 像这样
like initialization, like this.
看上面这里 显示的是
And now, up here. See where it says
implementation PlayingCardView
"Implementation PlayingCardView?"
如果我单击它 看到这里加了一条线吗
If I click on that, you see how it's put a line here?
这个破折号就是这条线
That's this dash is this line,
initialization显示在这里
and then Initialization appears here,
将这些方法分成了一组
and it's grouped these for me.
我可以在上面这里也加上
So, I can put, like up here as well,
#pragma mark - Drawing
pound sign pragma, mark Drawing.
还可以加在这
And maybe up here,
#pragma mark - Properties
I could put pound sign pragma, mark Properties.
这样这些方法就很好地分组显示了
And then my stuff really gets nicely grouped, okay?
可以考虑用这个方法
So, something to think about there.
好了 回到这里
All right, so back to here.
现在我的背景色是白色
So, now I've got my background white
显示在一个圆角矩形中 非常好
in a rounded rect, which is great.
但我还想在卡牌边缘
But I actually also want to draw a little black line
添加一圈黑色边框
around the edge of my card.
怎么做呢
Okay? So how would I do that?
非常非常简单
Very, very, very simple.
我只要设置描边颜色
I'm just going to set my stroke color
[[UIColor blackColor] setStroke]
which is UIColor blackColor setStroke.
然后让roundedRect
And then I'm going to ask this roundedRect thing,
让这个贝塞尔路径描边
this Bezier path, to stroke.
它的线宽是默认值
Okay? And this can have the default line width,
可能是1 正是我想要的
which is probably one point, which is what I want,
但可以让线条变粗之类的
but I could make it thicker or whatever.
我们运行一下
So let's go ahead and run, and see what--
看看目前是什么样子
how things look so far.
现在是不会正常显示的
Now, this is not going to work.
我是故意的
And I'm doing this intentionally,
因为你们可能也会犯同样的错误
because you'll probably do the same thing.
缩小一点 好了
Let's put this down here. There we go.
好奇怪 为什么不行 好了
Surprised that doesn't do that. Okay.
可以看到 矩形没有圆角
So, you can see that I don't have my rounded corners,
也没有黑色边框
and I don't have a black line.
为什么呢
Why is this?
有谁知道吗
Anybody know?
因为没有连接类
Because you didn't hook up the class.
没错 因为我没有连接类
Exactly, because I didn't hook up the class.
如果我回到storyboard这里
Okay, so if I go back to my storyboard here,
它还是一个普通的UIView
this is still a plain UIView.
看到了吗 UIView
You see? UIView.
我需要把它改为PlayingCardView
So I need to change this to be a PlayingCardView.
现在再运行时
Now, when I run
系统知道它是一个PlayingCardView
the system knows that's a PlayingCardView
出现了好看的圆角
and I get nice, rounded rects.
看到四角被切掉了吗
Okay? See my corners cut off there?
都很好
It's all good.
外面有一圈黑色边框
And there is a little black line around there.
很难看清 但是有的
It's hard to see, but it's there.
好了 这部分完成了
Okay? All right, so we're off and running here.
下面我要绘制牌角
The next thing I'm going to do is draw the corners.
就是写着梅花A的那个地方
You know, like where it says ace of clubs?
在牌角有一个A
And in the corner there is an ace,
下面是一个梅花
and then underneath is a club,
在与之相对的那个角上是一个倒A
and then down in the other corner is upside-down ace,
然后上面是梅花
and then clubs above it.
知道我说的扑克牌是什么样的吧
You know what I'm talking about in a playing card?
我们要把它绘制出来
So, we're going to draw that.
方法是...
I'm going to do that by saying--
同样 扩大点空间
Again, let's make more space here.
我要写self drawCorners
I'm going to say self drawCorners,
用一个不同的方法来完成
but do this in a different method,
(void) drawCorners
void drawCorners.
想要实现它
Okay. So, to do this,
我需要用NSAttributedString
I'm going to use NSAttributedString.
我要做的是
Okay? And what I'm going to do is
将要放在左上角的
I'm going to make the string
那个字符串设为
that I'm going to put in that upper corner
A 回车 梅花
be ace, carriage return, clubs.
我要把它
Okay? So, I'm just going to put that
放在左上角
in the upper left corner.
这就是我需要的全部内容
Bingo, that's all I need.
但在属性化字符串中
But, I-- there's two things I need to set
有两项需要设置
in my attributed string.
一是字体
One is the font,
我要用预设字体
and I'm going to use preferred font,
二是我需要将段落样式设为居中
and number two is, I need the paragraph style to be centered.
我希望A和梅花
I want those two things, the ace and the club,
上下对齐居中
to be centered on top of each other.
我不想让它们左对齐
I don't want them to be left aligned,
那样看起来会很奇怪
that's going to look weird.
尤其是梅花10这种会看起来很搞笑
Especially like a 10 of clubs would look really funny.
我想让它们居中
I want them centered.
我们没讲过如何在属性化字符串中
So, we didn't really talk about how to set that kind
实现段落对齐等等
of paragraph-level alignment and stuff in a attribute string,
正好可以演示一下
so here's a chance to show you.
想要实现这个功能
So, to do that,
我们用这个ParagraphStyle类
we use this class called paragraph style.
它指定了
Okay, paragraph style specifies things
段落的对齐方式等
like the alignment of a paragraph.
所以我要创建一个它的可变版本
So I'm going to create a mutable one
这样就能进行设置了
that I can set things in,
方法是[NSMutableParagraphStyle alloc] init]
and I do that with NSMutableParagraphStyle, alloc init.
然后将paragraphStyle的对齐属性
And then, I'm going to set the paragraphStyle's alignment
设为NSTextAlignmentCenter
to be NSTextAlignmentCenter.
表示居中
So that just mean centered.
然后我要在属性化字符串中
And then I'm going to set this
将它作为属性 进行设置
as an attribute on my attributed string.
我还需要一个字体属性
The other attribute I need is the font,
在这里创建一个cornerFont
so I'm going to say a cornerFont here, and--
打错了是Font
whoops, font--
当然我需要用预设字体
and I need, of course, to use a preferred font.
这有些参数
And, you know, there's some arguments here.
最适合这里的样式是什么呢
What would be the best style here?
标题样式吗 还是副标题样式
You know, maybe Headline, maybe even subHeadline.
但我要试试正文样式 看看是什么样
But I'm going to try Body, and we'll see how it looks.
如果我不喜欢
And if I don't like it,
可以再改成别的样式
I can go change it to something else.
但是关于这个字体
But there's something really important
有一点很重要 需要注意
to notice about this font.
它会以特定大小显示
It's going to come in in a certain size,
用户可以随意选择
whatever size the user wants,
像我这样上岁数的人想要大字 好看清
old people like me want big ones, so I can see.
像你们这样的年轻人可能想要小字
And younger people like you probably want smaller ones.
但我们还要在此基础上对它进行缩放
But we still need to scale it from there.
我们要用预设字体大小的信息
So, we want to use that information,
但还要对它进行缩放
but then we want to scale it
同样取决于卡牌的大小
again, depending on how big our card is.
大牌显示大字 小牌显示小字
Big cards want big font, little cards want little fonts.
实现它的缩放的方法
Okay. So, we're going to scale it
就是在这新建一个字体
just by creating a new font here.
我们要怎么做呢
And we're going to do that.
确认一下 要和我之前定好的方法一样
Make sure I do this the way that I predefined it here.
我要这样做
So, I'm going to do this
cornerFont fontWithSize
by saying cornerFont, fontWithSize.
它是字体的一个实例方法
So, this is a method in font, an instance method in font.
它会新建一个字体
This is create me a new font
和我发送给它的字体一样
that's just like the font I'm sending this to
但是大小不同
but with a different size.
我要用的大小是
And the size I'm going to use is
cornerFont的当前大小
cornerFont current size--
pointSize是字体的一个属性
pointSize is property in a font
能告诉你当前磅值是多少
that tells you what its current point size is--
用它乘以cornerScaleFactor
times that cornerScaleFactor
我之前用过的 在上面这里
that I used earlier, up here,
求cornerRadius时用到的
to do this cornerRadius, okay?
就是这个cornerScaleFactor
So this is this cornerScaleFactor.
用的是相同的比例系数
I'm using the same factor here.
我们会检查显示效果是否正确
And, again, we'll see if that turns out to be right,
如果不对 还可以修改
if not, we can always change it.
现在 我们来创建这个属性化字符串
So now, let's go ahead and create this attributed string.
我要叫它cornerText
I'm going to call this the cornerText, and I'm--
[NSAttributedString alloc] initWithString
it's just NSAttributedString, alloc, initWithString.
我要创建的字符串是NSString stringWithFormat
The string I'm going to create is NSString stringWithFormat,
就是刚才说过的 %@
%@
as I promised, % at sign, carriage return, % at sign.
第一个占位符是rank
Okay. The first thing is the rank.
这里要写self rankAsString
So, I need self rankAsString,
因为rank是一个数字
because my rank is a number,
需要把它转换为字符串
and I need it as a string.
我要到上面这里...
So I'm going to go up here and really--
出来了 rankAsString
whoop, look at that, rankAsString.
和之前做过的一样
So, same thing we did before,
一个排列数组 然后是self.rank
little array with that in there, self rank.
没有检查bounds之类的操作
I don't do any bounds checking and stuff,
这个示例缺少bounds检查
this demo is light on bounds checking.
好的代码会在自我保护上做的更好一些
You know, good code would protect yourself a little better.
然后是suit
And then, here is the suit.
suit
Okay? Suit, suit.
检查一下方括号对不对
All right, so make sure I have my square brackets right here.
self suit 不对 好了
self suit, no, and there we go.
这就是字符串
So, there's the string.
这里我们要设置的属性
And then, the attributes we're gonna
是一个dictionary
set here is a dictionary.
我要设置字体
And I need to set the font.
叫什么来着
Font-- what's it called again?
NSFontAttributeName
Font-- NSFontAttributeName.
然后是cornerFont
And that's the cornerFont right there.
然后是NSParagraphStyleAttribute
And then, I need NSParagraphStyle attribute,
这个大家没见过
which is a new one you haven't seen before
我们叫它paragraphStyle
and we'll call that paragraphStyle.
加上大括号
Okay, close curly brace.
错了 谢谢
Oops! Thank you.
删掉它
Delete that.
分号
Okay, semicolon.
对了吗
Are we good there?
我觉得可以了
I think we're good.
好了 这就是cornerText
Okay. So, there's the cornerText,
就是这个回车字符串
which is just this carriage return thing,
希望字体大小合适且居中
centered with the, hopefully, good-sized font.
现在我要得到它的bounds
And now, I'm going to get the bounds of that.
我要得到bounds
Okay? I'm going to get the bounds,
然后将它放进去
then I'm going to put that in.
bounds有两个参数
And there's two things to the bounds.
一是左上角那个点
One is the point, the upper left-hand point of it.
我可以直接...
And I could just make that be--
实际上 我甚至不需要用局部变量
actually, I don't even need a local variable.
就直接用textBounds.origin
Let's just go straight to bounds dot origin.
其实我可以将它设为(0,0)
So, I could make that be zero-zero, actually,
但这样的话 A回车梅花
but then my little A return clubs
可能会和roundedRect的边线重叠
might kind of bang into my roundedRect a little.
所以要把它往里移一点
So, I want to move it in a little bit,
这里同样要根据roundedRect的大小
but again, it depends on how big the roundedRect is
来决定往里移动的距离
to how much I want to move it in.
我们用CGPointMake
So let's say CGPointMake,
[self cornerOffset] [self cornerOffset]
how about self cornerOffset, self cornerOffset.
cornerOffset是我加在这里的另外一个方法
And cornerOffset is another little method I put up here
它也和cornerRadius有关
that's also related to this cornerRadius.
看到了吗 我用cornerRadius除以3
You see, I took the cornerRadius divided by 3.
看起来大概合适
That looks like that's probably about right.
你在设计UI时
Again, these are numbers you would want to play with
需要考虑这些数字
when you are designing your UI.
这些数字看起来还不错
These numbers seem to work pretty good.
而矩形的大小
And then, the size of this rectangle,
我要请求属性化字符串来告诉我
I actually need to ask the attributed string to tell me.
cornerText size
CornerText size.
那个A回车梅花要多大呢
You know, how big is that A return clubs going to be?
因为我不知道
Because I don't know. Right?
但属性化字符串可以告诉我
The attributed string can tell me, though.
现在我有了一个矩形
So, now I have a rectangle,
我要在里面绘制A回车梅花
and I'm going to drew the A return clubs in,
二者水平居中
and it's going to be centered horizontally on it.
我只要让它绘制
And all I need to do is tell it to draw.
cornerText drawInRect: textBounds
CornerText drawInRect: textBounds.
这样它就在矩形中绘制了
Okay? So now it's drawing in that rect.
会在那个矩形中进行文字对齐
So it's gonna be doing the text alignment inside that rectangle.
就是这些
Okay? So that's it.
希望运行正常
Let's hope this works.
这不对
And it doesn't work.
为什么不行呢
Now, why does this work-- not work?
因为我们还没有设置卡牌
Well, because we haven't set any card.
这个PlayingCardView没有显示特定卡牌
This PlayingCardView is not displaying any particular card.
所以我们要回到视图控制器
So, we need to go back to our view controller
对卡牌进行设置
and set that card to something.
现在想要测试一下的话
And a great place to do that
有一个地方很合适
for testing right now anyway,
就是在viewDidLoad中
is in viewDidLoad.
我们只要选择一种卡牌
So, we're just going to pick a particular one.
还要添加一个到卡牌的输出口
We also need to make an outlet to our card here,
这样才能向它发送消息
so we can talk to it.
从左边这里开始 到右边
So we're going to start here, and then go over here.
按住control键拖拽到右边 创建输出口
I'm going to control-drag to create an outlet.
我要叫它playingCardView
I'm going to call it playingCardView.
这是一个输出口
Okay, so here's an outlet,
拉大一点 看得更清楚
so you can see what this is about.
这是一个输出口 IBOutlet
Okay. This is an outlet, IBOutlet.
它是PlayingCardView
It's a PlayingCardView,
所以需要导入PlayingCardView
so we need to import PlayingCardView.
这样就能用了 很好
All right, so that works. That's good.
我们有了playingCardView
We have our playingCardView,
我只要设置playingCardView
so I'm just going to set my playing card--
self.playingCardView
self.playingCardView.
将它的suit设为红桃
I'm going to set its suit to be hearts,
将rank设为K
and then I'm going to set its rank to be king.
这是我最喜欢的牌 红桃K
Okay, that's my favorite card, king of hearts.
在这里添加一个心形
So, let's set this to hearts.
选择特殊字符
Special characters.
这个心形
There's a heart.
没选上
Oop, missed it.
特殊字符 心形在这里
Characters. There's a heart.
这回选上了吗
Did I get it that time?
好了 红桃K设好了
Yeah. Okay, so there's a king of hearts,
我们要显示这张牌
so we're going to do that.
运行一下
So, now we run.
希望能显示出红桃K
And we should hopefully get the king of hearts.
出来了
There it is.
大小看起来很合适
And the sizes look pretty good there.
如果对它进行调试
Okay. Now, if I were debugging this--
我们直接做一下吧
In fact, let's just do it.
把牌缩到很小 看会怎么样
Let's make this card really small, see what happens.
试一下
Let's try this.
看起来也不错
And that looked good, too.
成功了 我很开心
Okay, so I'm pretty happy with that.
我还应该再转到设置页面
And then, I would also want to go to settings
将字体变大和变小
and set the fonts bigger and smaller,
检查是否能正常显示
and make sure that still works.
但是现在这样我已经很满意了
But, you know, I'm so far pretty darn happy with it.
当然了 我来之前检查过了
Now, of course, I checked this before I came today.
课上就不做了
I'm not gonna do these on the fly.
好了
So, there we go.
下面我们要做什么呢
Now, what do we need to do next?
现在我们要把那个红桃K
Well, now we need to put that king of hearts
上下颠倒 放在右下角
in the other corner, upside-down.
你可能会想 太好了 上下颠倒
Okay, now you might think, "Oh great, upside-down.
怎么做呢
Well, how are we going to do this?"
在Core Graphics中
Turns out to be very, very easy to rotate
要旋转绘制内容非常简单
what you draw in Core Graphics.
我们来做一下
So, we're just going to do that.
和刚才的操作都一样
We're just gonna do exactly what we just did
但是要旋转至上下颠倒
but rotate it upside-down.
回到这里
So I'm going to go back here.
还要做同样的操作 这个drawInRect
I'm going to do this same thing, this drawInRect.
但执行这步之前 在这里
Okay? But before I do it, inside here,
我要将它旋转至上下颠倒
I'm going to rotate it upside down.
首先移到右下角
First, I'm going to move down to that corner,
然后旋转至上下颠倒
then I'm going to rotate upside-down.
如何移到一角呢
So, how do we move over to a corner?
我们用一个CG函数
Well, let's use one of these CG functions
这就是我说的用到上下文的地方
that I told you you needed the context for.
用ContextRef
So, let's get a contextRef.
context=UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext()
Context equals UIGraphicsGetCurrentContext.
我讲了 这是得到当前上下文的方法
I told you that's how you get the current context.
得到它之后 我可以用CGTrans...
Now that I have it, I can use CGTrans--
叫什么来着 有人记得吗
What's it called? Anybody remember?
ContextTranslate什么的
Translate something, ContextTranslate something.
找到了
There we go.
TranslateCTM
TranslateCTM.
CTM表示变换矩阵
CTM is our transformation matrix.
我们要转移它
Okay, so we're just going to translate,
也就是移动它
which means move it.
目标位置是
So I'm going to move it down
self.bounds.width, self.bounds.height
to self.bounds.width and self.bounds.height.
移动到右下角
Okay, move down to the corner there.
我输错了吗
Oops! Did I type something wrong?
忘了size
Size, oops, size, size.
self.bounds.size.width, self.bounds.size.heigth
Okay, self.bounds.size.width, self.bounds.size.heigth.
我要移动到右下角
So, I'm moving down to the bottom corner there
要记住 原点是左上角
Remember our origin is in the upper left.
现在来旋转
And now, let's rotate.
用CGContextRotateCTM context
There's a RotateCTM context
然后是旋转弧度
and this is radians.
我要旋转半圈
So, I'm going to go halfway around,
就是要上下颠倒
in other words, upside-down,
也就是M_PI
which is m underbar PI.
π弧度是半圈180度
Pi radians is halfway around a circle.
我想让它上下颠倒
I want it to be upside-down, directly upside-down,
从开始位置旋转180度
180 degrees from where it was before.
就是这样
And, that's it. Okay?
我移动并旋转了要绘制的内容
So, I've translated and rotated what I wanted to draw.
然后我只要再绘制一遍就行了
And then, I'm just gonna draw the exact same thing again.
很好 没问题
Bingo! Okay?
Core Graphics中的某些操作真的很容易实现
So, some stuff is really, really easy to do in Core Graphics.
旋转 移动 特别容易
Okay? Rotating, translating things, super-duper easy.
明白吗 这部分做完了
All right? So, we're good there.
下面我们要做的是
Okay, the next thing we want to do
绘制牌面
is draw the face of the card.
红桃K的牌面
Okay? That king of hearts face.
扑克牌的牌面有两种
Now, the face of the card is one of two ways,
一种是人头牌 比如K
either it's a face card, like the king,
另一种就是花色符号组成的
or it's just the pips, right?
比如红桃4的牌面就是四个小心形图案
Like the four of hears is four little hearts in there.
两种我们都要做
Okay, so we have to do both ways.
先做人头牌
So, let's do the face card one first.
我要在上面这里完成
Okay, so I'm going to do that up here,
回到drawRect方法
back in drawRect.
在drawRect方法中
So, I'm in drawRect.
我要做的是
And what I'm going to do,
我要在这里添加一组条件判断
I'm just gonna kind of have a design here
如果能找到
where if I can find an image
和牌名相同的图像
that has the name of the card,
就直接用它
I'll use it.
否则就绘制花色符号
Otherwise, I'll try and draw pips,
否则就什么都不绘制
otherwise, I'll draw nothing.
这种方法挺安全的
Okay, so it's kind of a fairly safe way to go about it.
如果我找不到牌面图像 就不绘制了
If I can't find the face card image, then it'll just be--
两个角的内容还在
I'll still have the corners,
但牌面上不会有任何图案
but I won't have any drawing.
要怎么实现呢
So, how am I going to do that?
先查找图像
I'm just going to look up the image.
用UIImage
I'm going to say UIImage--
再扩大点空间
Let's make more space again.
UIImage faceImage
UIImage, faceImage,
UIImage imageNamed:
and I'm going to say UIImage, imageNamed,
然后创建一个字符串 stringWithFormat
then I'm going to make a string, stringWithFormat.
占位符分别为rank和suit
And it's going to have the rank and the suit.
[self rankAsString] self.suit
Okay, self rankAsString, self.suit.
这就是图像名称
Okay. So, there's the image name.
我要查找这个名称的图像
So, I'm going to look that image up,
比如黑桃J
so that would be like, J spades, right?
红桃10没有对应图像
10 hearts is not going to find 10 hearts.
没有它的图
There's not going to be such thing,
但是有梅花K
but there will be K clubs, right?
可以找到这种的
It'll find those.
如果找到了牌面图像
So, if it finds the face image,
我就要把它显示在中间
then I'm going to display it in the middle,
否则 我就要绘制花色符号
otherwise, I need to draw the pips, basically,
因为它不是人头牌
because it's not a face card.
在这里添加一个drawPips方法
So let's put a little drawPips here.
等会实现它
Okay, do that later.
牌面图像
So, the face image.
要怎么显示出来呢
How do I do this?
我只要告诉UIImage
Well, really I just need to tell UIImage
将这幅图绘制在卡牌中间
draw this in the middle of my card.
但我想让它缩进去 离开边缘一点
But I want to move it in from the edges a little bit, right?
因为我不想让牌面图像
Because I don't want whatever the face image is,
比如K的国王图像 破坏了两个角的图像
like a king, to smash my corners.
红桃K上的国王
Okay? My little king of hearts.
我想让图像缩进去一点
So, I want to move it in a little bit,
所以我要新建一个矩形
so I'm going to create a rectangle
让图像在其中进行缩放 叫imageRect
to scale my image into, imageRect,
基本上是我的bounds
and it's going to basically be my bounds,
但我要用这个CGRectInset方法
except for I'm gonna use this CGRectInset method here
让它缩进去进去一点
to inset it just a little bit.
缩进的距离是
And I'm going to inset it
self.bounds.size.width
by self.bounds.size.width
乘以 1减去一个新建属性
times 1.0 minus a new property that I'm gonna invent,
叫做faceCardScaleFactor
called faceCardScaleFactor.
faceCardScaleFactor如果是0.9
So, the faceCardScaleFactor is going to be like .9,
代表卡牌大小的90%
to be 90% of the size of my card.
0.9表示卡牌大小的90%
Okay, .9 would be 90% of the size of the card.
size.height也一样
And then, same thing with size.height.
height 抱歉
Oops! Height. Sorry.
一样的 用height乘以
Height times-- same thing,
1.0-self.faceCardScaleFactor
1.0 minus self.faceCardScaleFactor.
好了 我们要添加这个属性
All right, and we have to go make this property.
来做一下
So, let's go do that.
放到上面这里 属性组第二个
Let's go up here, put it in our properties second.
我又快速地打好了
And I'll type it really fast, again.
抱歉用这个方式
Sorry to have to use those,
但有时候打字很无聊
but somethings are boring to type.
好了 我添加了这个faceCardScaleFactor
All right, so I have this faceCardScaleFactor.
它是一个浮点数
It's a float.
我要重写setter和getter
I'm going to override both the setter and the getter.
在getter中 我要确保
Okay? In the getter, I'm going to make sure that
它至少有一个默认值
it's at least a default value.
默认值是90%
Okay? 90% is going to be my default value,
它至少是这个默认值
so it's at least going to be that default value.
而在setter中 我要调用setNeedsDisplay
And in my setter, I'm going to call setNeedsDisplay.
因为如果有人设定了比例系数
Because if someone sets that scaling,
如果是人头牌 就需要重绘卡牌
I got it to redraw my card if it's a face card.
大家明白吗
Okay? Everyone understand this?
因为setter和getter我都要做
And since I do both the setter and the getter,
那我需要做什么呢 synthesize
look what I have to do, synthesize.
大家还记得吗
Okay? Everyone remember that?
如果同时用到了setter和getter
If you put in both the setter and getter,
你就得synthesize自己
you've got to synthesize yourself.
好好回想一下
Okay, good reminder of that.
现在我有了这个imageRect
Okay, so now I have this imageRect,
按照百分比向内缩小
and it's inset by that-- whatever that percent is,
如果是90% 就是1-90%
10% if it's-- you know, 90 would be 1.0 minus that,
也就是宽度的10% 高度的10%
10% of my width, 10% of my height.
现在我可以直接用faceImage drawInRect:imageRect
And so, now I just say faceImage, drawInRect: imageRect.
它就将图像缩放到适合那个矩形的大小
Okay? And it will scale it to fit in that rect.
我需要这些图像 我们来添加一些
Now, I need these images, so let's go grab those.
我正好有 在这里
I happen to have them handy right here.
这些图片
Okay? So, here's a bunch of images
就是人头牌对应的图像
that I have for face cards.
把它们拖拽到
Let's just go ahead and drag them
资产库中 图像资产
into our assets library here, image assets.
这就是我们的图像资产库
So, here's our image asset library.
还什么都没有
We don't have any yet.
把它们拖进来
Drag that in there.
正好在这 顺便再把斯坦福大学图标拖进来
While I'm here, I'm also gonna drag our famous Stanford one.
这个高分辨率的图标也拖进来
And, actually, let's get the high-res one, too.
我们还要把它作为卡牌背面图案
Okay, we'll use that as our card back again.
所有图像都在这里了
Okay, so we got all our images here.
这些图像 看这个
So, the images. Look at this.
我们再放一张高分辨率的人头牌图像
Let's put the high-res one in
至少加一张红桃K的
for a king of hearts, at least.
现在这是红桃K的
So here's the king of hearts.
这些图的高分辨率版本我都有
I have a high-res for all of them,
但时间有限
but just for time constraints,
我们就只把它放到这里
let's go ahead and put this guy right here.
至少加上这张
Okay, so we get that one at least.
好的
All right.
我想把它们都拖进来
I'd want to drag them all in for all.
但就这样吧 现在我有了这些图片
But anyway, so now I have these images.
现在再运行时 它会去查找
So now, when I run, it's going to go look
这些名称对应的图片
for the image of these names, you see?
就会找到红桃K这张
And it's going to find the king of hearts there.
就是这位自杀的国王
Okay? So, that's the suicide king.
看起来很不错 大小很合适
Right? Looks pretty decent. Size is pretty good.
现在我们要快速地做两件事情
Okay. All right, so now we are going to do two quick things.
我知道时间快到了
I know we're right on the edge of time here.
我们快速地做一下手势识别器
We're going to do the gesture recognizers really quick.
我要做两件事
So I'm going to do two things.
一是 让这个PlayingCardView在运行时牌面向下
One is, let's make this PlayingCardView work facedown.
方法是判断现在是否牌面向上
And we're just going to do that by saying if we're face up,
如果是的话 就执行这段代码
then we'll do this, all this stuff.
否则就显示背景图片
Otherwise, we will just do our background image,
UIImage imageNamed: 最爱的cardback
UIImage, imageNamed, favorite cardback.
我要把它改名为cardback
I'm going to change it to that.
然后是drawInRect self.bounds
And then drawInRect, self.Bounds,
背景图的牌角没有图案
and then for the back, I don't have the corners.
我可以直接用整张图
And so, I can just go ahead and use the whole thing,
改成cardback
so cardback.
这样扑克牌背面图案就设好了
Okay, so now we have the front-- the back there, rather.
运行时 它是牌面向下的
So now, since it's face up-- it starts out not face up.
所以是这样的 但我需要把它翻过来
So, here it is, but I need to flip this over.
我们用滑动手势将卡牌翻过来
So let's do a swipe gesture to flip that over.
我们用Xcode来添加滑动手势
Okay, and the swipe gesture we're going to do using Xcode.
方法是这样的
Okay? So, swipe gestures go like this.
转到右下方的对象面板
You go down here, you get in the object palette,
按钮所在的地方
same place buttons are,
可以看到这里有这些手势
and you'll see that there's these gestures here.
选中滑动手势
Now, I'm going to take a swipe gesture
将它拖拽到
and drag it onto the view
要识别这个滑动手势的视图上
that I want to recognize that swipe,
显然是PlayingCardView
which is my PlayingCardView, obviously.
然后我只要从这个小图标进行control拖拽
Then, I simply control-drag from this little icon
下面的这个小图标
that appears down here.
看到了吗
You see it?
代表滑动手势
Swipe gesture.
还可以从这里进行拖拽
You can also do it from here,
在这个文档大纲中
this little document outline
今天我们没有时间讲这个了
which we don't have time to talk about today.
但是可以这样做
Okay, but you can do that, too.
我要从这里按住control键进行拖拽
But I'm going to control-drag from here.
选择自动模式下的控制器
Oops! Go auto in controller.
只要拖拽过来就可以了
And you just drag that.
非常像目标操作
It's very much like target-action.
我要加它swipe 比较直观
Okay. I'll call this a swipe, just to make it clear.
类型参数是UISwipeGestureRecognizer
And their argument is the swipe gesture recognizer.
不知道为什么默认值不是它
I'm not sure why it doesn't default to that.
这样就添加了swipe
And we have the swipe.
在swipe中 我们只要这样做
And the swipe, all we need to do
self.playingCardView.faceUp
is say self.playingCardView.faceUp
=!self.playingCardView.faceUp
equals not self.playingCardView.faceUp.
只要把扑克牌翻过来
Just flip it over. Okay?
出来了
Here it is.
我要滑动
I'm going to swipe, okay.
默认滑动方向是向右的
The default swipe direction, by the way, is to the right,
随着滑动 大家可以看到
so I'm swiping and you can see
扑克牌翻过来又翻回去
that it's flipping the card back and forth.
还可以检查滑动方向
By the way, you can inspect which direction the swipe is
只要选中它 转到检查器
by clicking on it and going to the inspector.
列表中有右 左 上 下四个方向
Then there's right, left, up, down,
回答了刚才的问题
so that answers your questions,
只有这四个方向
those are the only four there are.
还有用到几根手指
And how many fingers have to be involved,
一指 多指等等
one finger, multiple fingers, etcetera.
最后 我要添加一个捏合手势
Okay? And lastly, I'm going to do a pinch gesture,
捏合手势的实现部分
and I'm going to do the implementation,
我要全部在视图中完成
the pinch gesture, entirely in the view, okay?
所以我要在视图中新建一个方法
So I'm going to add a new method to the view,
叫做pinch
which is pinch.
它是一个UIPinchGestureRecognizer
And it's going to be UIPinchGestureRecognizer.
这个pinch非常简单
Okay? Now, this pinch is really simple.
它只要判断
It's just going to say
手势的状态是否为Changed
if the gesture's state is changed--
不是Began 是Changed
oops, not Began, Changed,
或者为Ended
or if the gesture's state is ended.
然后只要
Okay? Then, I'm simply going to
用我的faceCardScaleFactor
take this faceCardScaleFactor that I have
乘以gesture的scale
and multiply it by the gesture scale.
但我不希望结果累积
But I don't want that to accumulate,
所以每次都要将gesture的scale
so I'm going to set the gesture's scale
重置为1.0
back to 1.0 all the time.
下次被调用时
So, the next time I get called,
得到的是增量的缩放比例
I'll get the incremental scale.
全部需要的就是这些
Okay? So, that's all that's necessary there.
我要让它成为公有的
I'm actually going to make this public,
因为我想将这个手势识别器
because I want to be able to
添加到控制器中
add this gesture recognizer in my controller.
我们就加到这里
So, let's just add this here, just so my gesture--
这样我的控制器就知道
so my controller knows that
卡牌视图可以识别这个手势
my card view is capable of this.
然后只要转到viewDidLoad
Then, I simply go in viewDidLoad,
self.playingCardView addGestureRecognizer
and say self.PlayingCardView, addGestureRecognizer.
新建一个UIPinchGestureRecognizer
And I'm just gonna create a new UIPinchGestureRecognizer,
alloc init
alloc, init.
这是指定初始化方法
You'll see that this is the designated initializer,
目标是视图
the target is going to be the view,
操作是pinch
and the action is going to be pinch.
好了 就是这样
Okay. Well, that's it.
就是这样在代码中添加手势的
So, this is how you add this in code.
都明白吗
Everyone understand this?
我将它添加到这个视图中 创建它
So, I'm adding it to this view, creating it.
这是目标
This is the target.
视图会处理它
The view is going to handle it.
它会处理捏合手势
It's going to handle the pinch.
我们处理了滑动手势
We handled the swipe,
但是捏合手势是由视图处理的
but the view is going to handle the pinch.
我们看一下效果如何
All right, so let's see, what does that do?
如果这里有张牌 如果进行捏合缩放
That should allow us, when we have a card here,
可以改变它的大小
if I pinch, to change the size,
因为它是在调整faceCardScaleFactor
because it's adjusting that faceCardScaleFactor.
看到了吗
You see?
明白吗
Make sense?
要添加deck
But, all we need to do to add the deck here
我们只要回到控制器
is to go back to our controller and add --
先把模型拖进来
Well, first of all, let me drag the model in.
我的模型在这里
I've got my model right here.
这就是我的模型 和Machismo中用过的一样
There's my model. Same model we used in Machismo.
我只要在这里添加deck
And I'm just going to go here and add that deck,
[strong, nonatomic] Deck *deck
strong nonatomic, Deck star deck.
导入PlayingCardDeck
Let's go ahead and import PlayingCardDeck,
导入PlayingCard
let's also import PlayingCard.
deck设好了
All right, so now we have that deck.
这是deck的延迟实例化
Here is the lazy instantiation of the deck,
你们知道的
you know about that.
我还要添加一个方法
I'm also going to have this method
叫做drawRandomPlayingCard
I'm going to call drawRandomPlayingCard.
这个方法
Okay, this method is just gonna
会从deck中绘制一张卡牌
draw a card from that deck.
判断它是否为一张扑克牌
It's gonna see if it's a playing card,
如果是的话 就把它放上去
if it is, it's going to cast it
所以有一个局部变量
so that we have a local variable.
然后进行赋值
Then it's going to set that
将PlayingCardView的rank和suit
in the PlayingCardView's rank and suit
设为card的rank和suit
to the card's rank and suit.
每次滑动并且牌面向下时
Okay? And I'm going to do that every time we swipe
都会执行它
and it's face down.
就是这样
Okay? So that's that.
出来了
So, here it is.
现在滑动时 会得到不同的扑克牌
So now when we swipe over, we get different cards.
我们还没有添加花色符号
Okay, we have no pips yet.
等会就做
I'm going to do that in a second.
但是有人头牌
But we do have the face cards,
这是方块J 分辨率有点低
the jack of diamonds, kind of low-res,
因为我没有把高分辨率的图片加进来
because I didn't have the other ones in there.
梅花K 不错
King of clubs, okay.
现在我们快速做一下花色符号
Now let's do the pips real quick.
花色符号非常简单
The pips are super simple,
如果已经有了一小段代码就更好了
especially if you have a little snippet here.
还记得这个drawPips吧
So, remember we have this drawPips, okay?
我直接把实现代码粘贴过来
I'm just gonna paste that with an implementation of that.
大家可以课下再看看花色符号这部分做了什么
You can go look at this offline, what pips does.
非常简单
Pretty straightforward.
就是用属性化字符串
It just uses attributed strings,
甚至只是用普通字符串来绘制
or maybe even just regular strings, to draw.
我们看看效果如何
So, let's see what that looks like.
这是我们的扑克牌
So, there's our card.
出来了 方块6
And there we go, six of diamonds,
梅花4 黑桃7
four of clubs, seven spades.
还有最后一件事要做
And the last thing I'm going to do.
调整视图的大小
Let's resize this view
看看我们修改了这么多内容之后
and make sure it still looks good small,
它是否还可以正常显示
even with all of the changes we made.
我们把它缩小到这么大
So, we'll make it, like, this big.
运行一下
And run.
看起来还不错
And it still looks okay,
花色部分看起来有点挤
a little squishy with the pips,
出来了一张人头牌 还不错
but I see a face card, that's not bad.
今天的内容就是这些
Okay, that's it for today.
抱歉拖堂了这么长时间
Sorry to keep you so long.
周一见
And I will see you all on Monday.
更多内容 请访问斯坦福网站
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.